Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, assorted destroyers of monsters.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host father Stephen D'Young is with me from Lafayette Louisiana, and I am father
editor Stephen Damick in Emas Pennsylvania, the great megalopolis of Eastern Pennsylvania.
And if you're listening to us live, you can call in at 855 AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
and it's taking a-
of calls tonight, which we're going to get to in the second part of our show. Before we get started,
I have a little advertisement to share. In this time, it's not for somebody else's thing. It is for
our thing on October 26th through 29th, 2023. So that's next year, assuming the world still exists
at that time. At the Antioch and Village in Western Pennsylvania in the little town of Ligonier,
We are going to be holding the first ever Lord of Spirit's conference.
Father Stephen and I are gonna both be there as well as father's David Subeu and Lucas Christensen
maybe more
Schedule still being worked on but you can find all the current details and you can register
By going to store dot ancient faith dot com slash events
bearing the lead
There's going to be a Dungeons and Dragons tournament
Probably.
No, there will be. It's in my right.
I said, don't worry about the green jelly beans, but there will be a deficit of
dragons tournament.
It may be me and eight attendees in the parking lot, but there will be one.
It's happening.
Yeah, yeah, it's going to be a lot of fun.
There should be at least one person dressed as a bat.
You know who you are.
Okay, moving on.
We continue our series tonight on the sacraments of the Orthodox Church by looking at
resumption.
So what is Christmas and what does it do?
How is Christmas used in the Old Testament?
Where is Christmas in the New Testament? Is it even a thing?
And what exactly does it have to do with the Holy Spirit?
So that's what we're talking about.
My first question though, is how many accidental references to cremation?
Are we going to make tonight? I've heard people call it that.
Well, this is cremated.
Yes, this is the shout out to my niece
who uh more than 20 years ago
What else we're pairing to be received into the Orthodox Church asked when his uncle Steve's cremation
She was ready for it. Yes. She has since been chrismated so and survived the experience baptism by fire
Right, so yes, we're gonna try to we're gonna try to avoid those and they are not the same thing. It's true
Yeah, so yeah, the first thing is like what
exactly is chrismation because especially if you're not orthodox that word might not be familiar to
you. Maybe it is, but it might not be. So what exactly is it? So chrism is a special oil that is
prepared by bishops and depending on which church you belong to of the orthodox church, you might
come from somewhere far away. It might also be more local. It's got a lot of different elements in
the recipe but that's not the important thing. The important thing is it
this special oil is then distributed to the priests.
And then they use that as part of baptism,
as part of receiving someone into the Orthodox church.
Right, it also gets used in some circumstances
for receiving converts whose baptisms are already considered
to be workable.
So that's what is, it's an anointing oil.
That's the a baptism.
It's considered to be a baptism, right?
It's an anointing oil and it's applied to the forehead,
Guys.
the ears, the mouth, nose. Now I'm going to miss the hands feet, chest back. Are you leaving
anything out? It's not that bad for much covers. That pretty much covers it. Yeah. It's also for
consecrating a church. Also used for consecrating churches. Alters. Alters. I've heard in some cases
that initial house blessings can include chrysalm as well. They do actually. You annoy the four
Four corners.
Yeah.
I know that. I might did an exorcism on a house, which I will know for the describe. I just leave that tantalizingly there. Yeah, absolutely. So that's Christmas.
And in the West done.
It's done normally as part of done to people right setting aside the cuts of creating a building.
It's done to people normally within the baptismal service.
Right. It's in tech.
the service. Yeah, so within that there are we probably should have done this earlier in our
series on sacraments. But in certain ways, drawing out these as independent sacraments is a little
artificial from an orthodox perspective.
Sure.
Yeah.
There is in the West,
a whole ordered theology of what is a sacrament and what is a sacramental and
then once you have that once you get into the Reformation era there are of
course disputes. Yes, right. Is this a sacrament? Is that not a sacrament? Yeah, you
get you get friend of the show John Calvin saying if you ever actually comes on
that would be amazing. But, um, Don Calvin? Yeah.
That would mean a whole lot of praying has been done for his soul.
For that to be possible.
Well, indoor necromancy, right?
Oh, there's.
Yeah.
It's okay.
I didn't want to throw that out there.
But no, um, John Keller, for example, you know, talks about the five
sacraments falsely so called nice.
But that's referring to the, uh,
The list of seven sacraments that became a fish.
within Roman Catholicism, with other things seen as sacramentals, there is not really such a list
in the Orthodox Church.
Yeah, I mean, I think you can find lists but it's not a super agreed upon thing that is
dogmatically declared by the Church, etc.
Right.
And the lists you find are usually lists in response to some Western interlocutor.
interlocutor. Yeah, yeah. And so, you know,
One big difference that people will probably notice is that sort of the parallel thing in the West is called confirmation, which usually is delayed until you're a teenager.
But early on in the Western Church's history, it was not delayed. We don't need to go into while all that is. But so it became this separate thing that was separated out from baptism.
But we don't do that. It's part of baptism for the Orthodox.
Right, right.
But because the the list don't sort of arise within the orthodox church organically
You get all different lists so you get lists with like 10 things you get lists with
Five things you get list with all these different numbers. I think I've heard that's 20 something on it. Yeah, but but also
Because there's a Western interlocutor
there's a tendency to sort of
line them up right with the person you're talking to.
Yeah, sure.
So you'll often see in like contemporary Orthodox discussions
of the sacraments or the mysteries that they're laid out is basically seven.
Even though we have things that are kind of parallel
the ones of the Roman Catholic.
church in a few instances but that are not exactly parallel. And this is one of them as you were
just mentioning, right? So part of the reason why even though naturally for us as Orthodox Christians,
you have baptism, chrismation and first communion altogether in one thing. Because those have been
split up in the West.
We tend to talk about them separately because of the Western interlock.
I mean, you know, and even baptism within itself as a, the service actually includes two separate
anointing.
It's kind of fun.
I don't sort of separate out that other one as another thing, you know.
Right.
Yeah.
Well, and there's Tonshure in there.
There's a whole bunch of things.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Right.
Those aren't sacrabbits of the west, they tend not to write.
Make them.
list. But so all that is to say, I'm anticipating some potential questions and responses. Right?
Because they naturally go together, there's not sort of this super firm line between, here's
what's going on in baptism and here's what's going on in chrysamation. Right? Right. The one does
XYZ, the other one does ABC, right? Because they're not now.
actually thought of as separate for us. So there's a blurry edge between the two because
of that. So this is to save everybody time in typing. Well, wait a minute, I thought
that was baptism or so, Christmas, it doesn't have a baptism doesn't. So then what if somebody's
Chris made it in a baptizer.
Yeah, he had it right.
Yeah.
Relax, right?
There's not a firm line between the two.
The important thing.
is that if you want to become Orthodox, you do whatever your priest tells you to do.
Yes. Yeah. Yeah. But so the core, the core thing, and like if you give the one sentence,
definition of what chrysmation is, it's that a person is anointed with oil,
this particular oil, but person is anointed with oil to receive the Holy Spirit.
That's the one sentence thing, right?
Of what?
What christmas is in the Orthodox Church.
And so everything we're going to say tonight now is going to be based on tracing the themes
related to that to both the reception of the Holy Spirit and anointing with oil through
the scriptures to show what that means.
All right, so where shall we begin?
We should begin at the beginning.
It's a very good place.
Roger's in Hammerstein told us.
It's a very good place to start.
And when those two guys agree.
So all the way back in Genesis 1, verse 2.
Right.
So almost as far back as we can go to the Bible,
That's
That's the first place where we see a direct reference to the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of God.
Yeah, from the beginning.
And when we first see him, it is actually a feminine imagery that's used of him because
Ruach in Hebrew is grammatically feminine.
Right.
And he is described as an English, it's usually translated as he's hovering over the waters.
That word for hovering in the Hebrew is actually a word that's used to describe a mother bird
brooding over its young or potentially young in the case of eggs in the nest.
And, say, Basil the great actually makes this point about it.
He doesn't know Hebrew, but he gets it through Syriac.
Oh, let's see.
No, he references the Syriac word.
Interesting.
Is it the hex I'm running?
Yeah, he references the Syriac word, which is available to him.
And Syriac for folks who don't know is a relatively late dialect of Aramaic.
And so he makes that same point based on the Syriac cognate word, right? But this imagery is also
also becomes important in terms of where the imagery is coming from as the Holy Spirit descending like
a dove at Christ's baptism.
Then as we've said on the show before.
He did not turn into a bird.
He did not.
It card a bird.
It's a symbolic bird you guys.
He descends like a dove.
His movement is like a dove.
Right.
And this is also describing movement or activity.
And as we've talked about before,
the creation before creations.
starts, which is where we are in Genesis 1 verse 2.
Right?
Creation is describing Genesis 1 as God putting things in order.
And so before that there is chaos.
But this sort of primordial chaos, or what Aristotle calls
prime matter, has the potential to be anything but isn't
anything.
And so that's partially contained in this.
bird imagery also, right? The brooding over the over the young.
Sort of the potentiality thing. Yeah.
The potential. This is going to become something, right?
It's going to hatch.
And that kind of language about the Spirit is all over the place like in our
Mattins service. Of the Holy Spirit is the one who gives life and breath.
Yeah, right. And that kind of ongoing...
creative power of the Holy Spirit.
And so we also see in Genesis 1,
a couple verses later, God starts to speak.
So when St. John at the beginning of his gospel says
that God created everything through his word,
right, that's a fairly literal reading of Genesis 1.
Yeah, right. They talked.
So you have
here already at the beginning of Genesis 1 you have God meaning the Father you have the logos
right the Word and you have the Spirit and the dynamic that's described in creation already in
Genesis is that the logos, right, and so ultimately Christ is the order into which
creation is brought. He's as principle that that defines how it's all supposed to be laid out.
Right. Right. And the Holy Spirit is the one who inhabits and in live ends that order.
Right. So creation happens through the sun, right, through the logos. And then through the action
of the holy
spirit, it is brought back to God the Creator. And yeah, we're throwing everybody in the
deep end right away in the first half at the beginning, which we normally don't do.
We normally wait for this kind of thing, but this time we're just going straight from
the deep end.
So, that's, and that's part of what, for example,
St. Aaronnaeus is getting at.
that dynamic in creation, that trinitarian dynamic in creation, is part of what
Saint-Erdace is getting at when he talks about the logos and the spirit as
the right and left hands of God.
There is this continual dynamic in creation.
The idea of Christ, the logos as the order into which creation is brought, is
not just connect.
to theosis as we've talked about it on the show, but that's where St. Maximus, when he talks about
everything in creation, having Logia. Yeah, there's a cosmic scale at which all this is happening.
Yeah, everything in creation has a Logia, that's all part of the logos, right? That's where he's
getting that. Right, so all kinds of things break down out of this, this understanding, this
is a trinitarian understanding of creation.
But important for us tonight, we're not gonna focus on all that because, you know,
I don't think, well, my co-host and our engineer don't want to stay here until 3am.
You got nothing else to do but I would be happy to, dear listener.
I would remain with you throughout the long, dark, cold night. But
but, um, this is everything called in Louisiana.
No, it was 82 today.
But it is dark.
But for our purposes here, we want to get at through this dynamic, what it means to be filled
with the Spirit.
What it means to be filled with the Holy Spirit.
And so the idea that the Holy Spirit inhabits and enlivens the created order.
On a cosmic scale tells us what that means.
And so from that, we get what that means on, for example, a personal basis.
And so first of all, right, that means to be truly alive is to be filled with the Holy
Spirit.
Hmm.
To be filled with life means to be filled with the Holy Spirit.
who is the Lord, the giver of life.
And it also means, right, that when someone is filled, as we've talked about on the episode
where we talked about what spirits are in general, right, that a spirit has agency, and so
a person who is filled with the spirit, then what they do is has the potential at least
to become God acting through them.
Yeah, cuz there's middle.
synergy. Right. God acting through them in a way that is transformative of them. Right.
So God loves people through them and that love transforms the person who is cooperating with
that love, for example. So when we move past creation and the creation of the world, we move
down from the level of the cosmos.
in the Old Testament. We move forward in the Old Testament a little further to where we have humans.
We see that there are certain people, certain individuals in the Old Testament
who are described as having been filled with the Holy Spirit on a at least potentially permanent basis.
Yeah, the Spirit is abiding in them or resting in them.
Right. Right.
Resting on them or in them or abiding in.
them or on them. And so an exhibit A of that is of course Moses. Yeah right. So Moses possesses
the Spirit of God. This is where the things that marks him out as a prophet. And the people in the
Old Testament who are described as being filled with the spirit on this potentially purr-
in it basis are by and large prophets. Yeah, because there's this job that God is giving
them to do. And so they need to be able to do it on an ongoing basis. Right. And they've
been in the presence of God, right? So they've met Christ. Right. And so now they've been sent
by him into the world, right, with this mission. And that's true to the point that
when we see
The other figures who possess the Holy Spirit on this potentially permanent basis, like David,
who's the king, he's not a prophet per se.
Yeah, he doesn't live out in the woods and have this weird opposing lifestyle.
Yeah, and Samuel and Nathan are around at that time and they're prophets, right?
depending on which point in David's life we're talking about.
Right.
But David is still described as a prophet.
And that's even within the pages of the New Testament.
It talks about David prophesying.
Yeah, the prophet king, right?
And that's because he is one of these who, in whom the Holy Spirit is dwelling.
And his father, Andrew mentioned that is what the Holy Spirit does in that prophet
it is a
and empower him to fulfill the role he's been sent to perform.
Yeah, it's not just like a personal possession,
like you're powered up, dude, now you're a superhero.
Yeah, yeah, it's not going super silent, right?
It's like a, it's like the sun for Superman.
It's the you,
The primary way in which.
that sort of empowerment, what that concretely means is, as we were saying, God acting through you.
Right? So it's not that God is giving you superpowers to perform your own mighty deeds. It's that God is going to, you've been called
to do these things and God is going to act through that person and that puts the
person who has received the Holy Spirit into a particular
relationship with God. Right? That is different than others who do not
similarly, I'm not similarly receive the Holy Spirit. Yeah, the function as
as his agent, but they have their own agency. It's not they're not being taken
over, but at the time. Yeah, not in this case. Right. At the same time, God is
is being an agent in them, you know, as well at the same time. Right.
Right. And this is why that relationship is often described in terms of sonship.
So the king in ancient Israel and Judah is the son of God in this adopted sense.
Yeah, because what do sons do? They have to be about the business of their father.
Right. So the son represents the father. Right. For as long as the father is alive.
Right.
Once the father's gone and the son becomes the head of the household, then his son's representing him.
That's the way ancient, we've got to think ancient extended families again.
So yeah, so it's important to emphasize, because even the language of agent can be kind of slippery.
Right.
because my agent can do things independently of me.
Right? There are different ways we talk about agent.
Right? So, I can talk about someone as my agent in a way that means they're going to do only what I tell them to do.
Right? We can talk about an agent as being someone who has the freedom to act on my behalf.
Right, and make their own decisions, but I'll be bound to those to see.
right, or we can talk about an agent as being the one sort of through whom I act.
And the agent has to cooperate in that case.
Yeah.
Right.
And so it's important that someone like this who has been called and sent on some particular mission
mission filled with the Holy Spirit to empower them in that mission is not
not then a free agent, pardon the pun.
It says that God is not binding himself to whatever they do.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right.
And God is not, but God also is not compelling.
Yeah.
Right.
That agent can still do things other than what God wants them to do.
Great. Right there. Oh, there heables to do.
that still. Stepping outside of that relationship if they do that. Right. And so rather it is the person
through whom God is going to act and what they do is they cooperate with that or they don't. Yeah. Right.
And you know, you don't have to read much of the Old Testament to see that folks often don't. But it is to as they say, winch the spirit. Right.
And so this is why
I said repeatedly as we got into this discussion that it is potentially permanent.
So King Saul, when he was anointed as King, was indwelt by the Holy Spirit to empower him
to be the King, over God's people.
But then there's a point in his life where the Holy Spirit departs from him.
Yeah, it says that in the scripture.
Right. And when we read Psalm 50 or 51 in the Hebrew, right, David's Psalm of repentance,
after his sin, he prays, do not take your Holy Spirit from me.
Because he knows it's a thing. Right. That's what happened to Saul. He could happen to him.
And he probably deserves for it to happen to him after what he's done. Right. Yeah.
And so that's part of his repentance is saying, you know, please
right? Because he's aware of his sort of dependence on God. So that's what I
say it's potentially permanent for these people in the Old Testament. There are
also instances in the Old Testament and people in the Old Testament who we see
the Holy Spirit abiding in or resting upon or filling.
on a sort of temporary basis. It still falls within empowering and in
liveening for a particular task that God wants to perform through them. But
that task is not like an ongoing thing like being king or being God's
prophet. It is for a sort of particular act for a particular time and place a
particular thing. Yeah, for a mission. Right.
and usually less than five years this mission.
So an example of that one example is in Numbers 11,
we read this passage at Great Vespers before the Feast of Pentecost,
where the Spirit who rested upon Moses permanently,
portions of it of the spirit come to rest on
the rest of the elders. Yeah, and they all begin to prophesy. And they all begin to prophesy. And
Joshua and some other Moses loyalists, right, get kind of offended, right? They're like, no,
Moses is the prophet. Tell them to stop, right? Yeah. Yeah. Moses says, no, I wish that all, right?
You know, the all of Israel could receive the spirit and prophesy. Is this the one where there's
the two guys that are
in the camp that they put it to. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, they showed up late for church. Yeah. I know that never happens now to anybody.
No, the Orthodox Church. But
the yeah, and so the reading actually ends right there with Moses saying that would that
all of Israel could receive the spirit prophesy for shadowing.
And then another example is in Exodus 31.
when bezel on the other craftsmen are contracted to build all of the things.
The arc, covenant and all the other stuff.
The second half of the book of Exodus is where everybody's...
Everybody starts to kind of fall asleep and get bored when they try to read straight through the Bible.
Sort of verbal blueprints.
Yeah. Well, and you get them twice.
So you get like the full detail of the blueprints.
and then you get the full details again
it describes them building the things from the blueprints. Yeah, right. All the measurements all
over again. But within that, just 31, those craftsmen who are doing the building from the blueprints
are filled with the spirit to enable and empower their work. Right. And so
So while the tabernacle is made by human hands it is.
You can also say that it is divinely created.
Right.
So, but there is nothing in the text to indicate
and everything to indicate otherwise that this wasn't sort of a permanent
kind of gift that Bezzalelle had,
so that sort of every chair he made for the rest of his life was holy.
A divine chair.
They did not become like a you know
myth god kind of figure. Yeah, yeah. So it's aimed at this one particular, this one particular task.
We also, I know we have mentioned at least briefly on the show before, the very creepy sounding
Holy Spirit possession. Yeah. And I think that term for it is purely based on people trying to
clickbait you into reading their scholarly articles.
Really?
Kind of like a couple of books of Joshua and judges.
Holy Spirit possession of Holy Spirit possession.
In ancient Israel.
So this is next.
Yeah.
This is an even,
it liked the previous examples is temporary.
But it tends to be even more temporary.
And the reason it's called Holy Spirit Possession, right?
The reason why you'd come up with another term for it is, in most of these, at least
implicitly and sometimes explicitly, the idea of human agency is removed.
Yeah.
Almost against their will.
Well...
maybe not against, that might be a little strong, or without their cooperation.
Right, right.
And the idea here being that these are acts that God does through a person that are being
characterized is purely God's act.
Yeah.
Right.
It's purely God who is doing this.
And so unsurprisingly, often these actions in terms of phenomena.
are things that would not normally be morally acceptable to people.
And what I mean by that is usually it involves smiting a whole lot of people.
Yeah, right. So like judges chapter three, verses 9 through 11, we have a smiting.
It says this. But when the people of Israel cried out to the Lord,
Lord raised up a deliverer for the people of Israel who saved them,
Othneal, the son of Knaz.
Caleb's younger brother.
The spirit of the Lord was upon him,
and he judged Israel.
He went out to war,
and the Lord gave Kusha Rishmothayam king of Mahanaharayam
into his hand,
and his hand prevailed over Kusha Rishmothayam.
So the land had rest 40 years,
then Othnial the son of Kanaz died.
You have to love the rhythm of those names, though.
And I may think of Ricky Tickey-Tavvy.
Yeah, it's the same
I'm kind of, kind of rhythm, you know.
Christian Rishataya of Mahana-Hurayam.
I would suggest someone named their child that,
but it would be a bad idea.
Because it's not dude.
Because it means what?
So Mahana-Hurayam is literally the place
between the rivers.
Okay, okay.
So it's a reference to Mesopotamia.
All right, all right.
Which means it's a reference to Babylon, et cetera, et cetera.
But Kushit Rishataya is probably not
His name is Mama.
gave him because it means it means the double dark evil one. So I mean if you name your
kid that, that's a lot to live up to. Right. Or down to is the case may be. But so this was
a bad dude. But what we see here is that that.
Caleb's younger brother, Othneal, who's the first of the judges of the book of judges,
is sort of seized by the Holy Spirit and then does a whole lot of killing.
And we use this as an example just because it's the first of the judges, but all through
the book of judges.
It's several times in the book of Joshua this happens.
You know, Shamgar, who's the next judge, ends up killing several hundred Philistines with an-
box code which is literally a pointy stick.
Right. Right after. But the idea here is that these actions are being
characterized as God's direct judgment. This isn't God gave this person permission
to engage in mass slaughter.
Yeah, right.
This is God.
judged this people and instead of using fire from heaven or the ground opening up and swallowing them or
and invading our brain of a neighboring empire he used shamgar in his pointy stick
right to a pretty great name though and shamgar is something you could name your kid
Oh yeah, what does that mean? I don't know if I can stop my head.
One of us-
You know, you could be Shamgar.
Shamgar.
I think that would mean foreign name.
Hmm.
If Gar is from Goore.
Anyway.
Um.
But yeah, Shamgar, not a lot of Shamgars.
No, I mean, I don't think I've ever met one, actually.
Yeah.
Um.
Othneal.
OK.
But Shamgar.
That's impressive.
That sounds like a barbarian name.
Yeah, right.
Probably because of that gar ending, which, which, I mean, in, in, in Old English,
gar means spear.
Larry.
And is the origin of her word garlic.
So maybe that's a very primitive version of the name Shakespeare.
Well.
So and this is.
as we talk about this issue of H.
agency, right? And partially here and partially as a
clarifier from our episode on spirits, that there's a
difference between a spirit and an idea in that and that
difference is that a spirit has agency. Yeah, right. That
the explicit difference. So we're talking about spirits.
spirit of a place, spirit of a group, the way we, the whole spirit's episode.
You go back and listen to it again.
That has a nature and a will and an agency, right?
An idea does not have that.
Ideas arise at particular times, in particular places, for particular reasons.
ideas are used by agents like humans or angels.
Ideas are used instrumentally. They're used as instruments. They're used as tools.
Yeah, they don't have an independent existence. It's like meaning. Meaning does not exist apart from those who mean.
Right. And we've talked about the news, right? The ideas, thoughts, present themselves, right, to the news.
Right. And so in the same way that color doesn't exist without an observer.
Right, they can see color. So if all the mantish shrimps die,
right, like 15 colors cease to exist.
Right. I mean, the fact that we wouldn't know the difference though.
Because there's we wouldn't, right.
But that's part of the point, because those colors don't exist apart from
right, the vision of the mantish shrimp.
Yeah.
That would be a great book title, The Vision of the Mantish shrimp.
So
The Holy Spirit obviously is not a holy idea.
Right. Right. That's a, yeah.
But that's also true of evil spirits. Right.
When we say that there are evil spirits motivating certain things happening in the world.
We don't just mean people have some bad ideas. Right.
Right. In fact, we're deliberately rejecting that interpretation.
Yeah, it's the general.
That is just a bunch of interplay with other beings.
Right.
This is not just a bunch of individuals who happen to have accepted bad ideas and agree with
each other and those ideas are making them do something horrible because ideas can't make
you do anything.
Yeah.
Right.
This is there are actual spiritual forces that have agency that motivate these things and
And one of the things that they use, right, is like...
a lever as an instrument to move human persons is ideas. They bring those ideas to the
fore. They tempt, they offer passions, they inflame passions, right? They do those things,
right? To get humans to use their agency in the world to do those things, right? But
the ideas themselves can't do that.
just ideas and in fact those ideas would not even arise if it weren't for those evil spiritual
beings. Yeah right right. The thought would not appear to a person to commit abominations
and atrocities if it were not right. So yeah, that's a clarification. It'll also relate to some
of the stuff we get into later this evening. So it was not totally just a random rabbit trail
and intersection. Right, right. Just mostly.
So this brings us, so we've talked about now in the Old Testament,
these sort of three levels of people being filled with the Holy Spirit,
the sort of potentially permanent, the temporary, and then sort of Holy Spirit possession
as a particular phenomenon.
That of course changes in the New Testament specifically at Pentecost.
I mean, can we just jump right to the New Testament in the first half?
Is that a thing?
Well, we're gonna jump back to the Old Testament two more toe
Okay.
It's not used to talk.
This is a tester, this is early out on the show.
So this is, we have departed from our usual structure.
I know, just throwing it left and right here.
Yes.
Our usual structure is more like the synoptic gospels
where we start someplace and take you on a journey.
This is a journey in two sound.
But tonight, this is more of a johanning structure
than it's kind of a spiral.
the spiral.
Yes, yes.
It's a series of cycles moving ever forward.
So yes, we are now segueing into the new testament, but don't worry, we'll be going back again.
We'll go back.
So but Pentecost, in order to correctly understand what's going on at Pentecost, we not only
have to have in mind what we just talked about. But also we need to talk about how
Pentecost was spoken of prophetically in the Old Testament.
Yeah, right, right.
So before we get to the New Testament, let's, let's stay in the Old Testament for just a
second.
We're still in mid-Segway.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
So, Joel chapter two, this is the classic bit and we read this at Pentecost, verses 28
and 29, and it shall come to pass afterward that I will pour out my spirit on all flesh.
your sons and your daughters show prophesy.
Your old...
men, shall dream dreams, and your young men shall see visions. Even on the male and female
servants in those days, I will pour out my spirit. And this is a difference from the way it works
in the Old Testament, right? Right. Right. And we actually read this twice at Pentecost because we read,
we read from Joel at Vestverse the Night Before and then this gets quoted in acts. Yeah, right.
So we end up reading it again.
But yeah, this is that primary look is and there's a big shift here, right? Because at all three of those levels of phenomena that we talked about,
the one thing that was consistent was we were always talking about individuals or small groups of individuals.
Yes, just certain special people.
But over against, right?
And this is, Joel is already emphasizing this difference, right?
Right.
it's all flesh, sons and daughters, young, old, right? And even on male and female
servants, right, it's actually slaves, right? They're saying everyone, everybody, right?
Um, if the, and, and so you have these, you know, male, female, you have old, young,
And then implied already is that, well, yeah, Kings would have it.
also slaves, which would be at the other end of the sort of social hierarchy, the socio-political hierarchy, right?
Yeah, and this is not only different from the way that it functions prior to this Neal Testament,
it's also going to be clearly different from the way that pagan religions understand
enlightenment or interaction with the gods and so forth. Is that suddenly now it's available to
every single person. And not just this esoteric elite. Right. Right. And but
But also a key difference all the way through.
This is part of why we're harping so much on agency, right?
Is that in those other cultures, right, these quote-unquote special people, right, the kings,
the heroes, the culture heroes, right, these people had a divine identity.
was a question of identity.
Yeah, right
Not a relationship
They were good fundamental difference
Right, it's a fundamental difference. So a
person filled with the Holy Spirit is not like the
neutral good version of a neutral evil giant, right?
These are different fundamentally different relationships
with the spirits in question.
right? Because the person filled with the Holy Spirit, again, that is not just a possession
of power that can be used how the person sees fit, and that does not identify all of their
actions as divine actions. Quite the opposite, right? There is a heightened potential for
judgment. Is what we see play out in the Old Testament. They had even in the New Testament.
I'm going to click.
you anonymize in Sapphire.
Right. Right. Right.
And so that's a fundamental difference.
It's a fundamental difference.
And that's the difference between what happens with
a nephilim and what happens with a saint who experiences
theosis.
Yeah.
Again, they're not just flip sides of the coin.
Right, they're fundamentally different.
things. So this we read from Joel because this is what gets quoted at Pentecost
in the Acts of the Apostles, but this idea of the Spirit coming to dwell within
everyone is fundamental to the all of the passages that talk about the new
covenant like in Jeremiah 31 and in parts of Ezekiel.
This is one of the marks of the new covenant being issued from the perspective of the prophets during and after the exile in particular.
That when the new covenant comes, there's going to be this shift and the Holy Spirit is going to come to dwell in everyone.
And then we see that take place on Pentecost with the apostles, with the people who hear the preaching of the apostles on the day of Pentecost.
in Jerusalem, but then that plays out in a very particular way through the rest of the book
of Acts in terms of people receiving the Holy Spirit.
And so there are exceptional instances, but the normal pattern, right, the normal pattern,
and you see this for example in Acts 8, 17 through 19 and Acts 9, verse 17 and 19 verse
is that someone...
has been baptized and then the Apostle lays hands upon them.
Yeah, and then that gives that person the Holy Spirit. That's the means through which that happens.
Right, and then the Holy Spirit comes into the person. Right after baptism, usually right after,
not in the case of the folks who were baptized by St John the Forerunner and didn't know who Jesus was.
Um, but for the most part, there's a little more time lag with those.
books, but and it's not an anointing at this point. It's just hands, hands right put on people by the apostles. Right.
And when you see an exception to that, that exception is there to make a point. So for example, one of the exceptions in the book of
acts is Cornelius. Okay. This is an insurion. Cornelius, this insurion receives the Holy Spirit before he is baptized.
And without the laying on of hands.
But why?
is that? Well, if you're reading acts, right, the whole build up to that is God sending
St. Peter to go see Cornelius and St. Peter's like the Gentile guy. Yeah. So this is a sign
for Peter, the Roman soldier, right? He has the whole vision, right, with the animals
and everything. And then even we get there, he's kind of tentative, right? And so every
but when he sees that Cornelius is how...
have received the Holy Spirit, the Spirit of God has come to dwell in them, then he's sort of like,
well, I mean, for Pete's sake, right? Like I intended. We need to just go ahead and baptize you,
right? Because clearly, right? This is the thing to do, sort of, it removes all doubts for him.
And then in X-15 he testifies to that.
And he uses that in X-15 talking to...
the other apostles to say, hey, they received the Holy Spirit, right? The Spirit of God comes to
dwell them. How can I not? Right? It baptizes them. So clearly God has chosen to do this among Gentiles as
well. So those are sort of exceptions that prove the rule, right? Or that point to the rule and help us
understand the rule. So the biggest question I think surrounding
this is okay we've talked about it like a theological level we talked about it
on a huge scope level in terms of the cosmos then on a smaller level with
individual persons in the Old Testament now we're getting well this is
potentially everyone who's who comes to Christ who's baptized right in the
new covenant. But what does this concretely do?
And a lot of the time when that question is asked and it's not just asked historically,
it'll be asked about chrismation now, right?
Yeah, like should I feel different?
Should I expect something to happen?
You know, like will I feel the whammy?
Yeah.
Is all of a sudden everything good and glow is right?
I mean, there are, there certainly are people who win their bathtub.
when they're concerned have various kinds of spiritual experiences and this isn't to make fun of that.
Yeah, right. It's a thing. But that is not primarily what happens, meaning we don't
crystal-bait people to give them the experience of receiving the Holy Spirit.
Yeah, as an experience. Yeah. Right. So that's not the aim, that's not the purpose,
That's something that sometimes accompanies it, right?
And so...
what are the things that this is actually doing according to the scriptures?
The first and most obvious is that the person begins to manifest the fruit of the
Spirit. Right. Love, joy, peace, etc. Patience, kindness, goodness, faithfulness,
gentleness, and self-control. There you go. I also know a sleepy, happy, grumpy,
dopey thingsy, bashful and talk.
Um, wow.
Dory.
Story.
Noree, or he's a real dwarf needs. But so I mean, that's sort of obvious. They're called
the fruit of the spirit, right? Right. Right. That's why they're called the fruit of the
spirit. You'll know by their fruits. I mean, it's funny. I think sometimes it's so,
I don't know, assumes the right word. But I've seen this sometimes, you know, that if
say, well, is this person showing the fruit of the spirit like, well, that doesn't matter
what matters is that they're right about this. You know, something like, well, the scripture
kind of says, you know, you'll know them by their fruits. So it's okay to look at the fruits, you know.
Yeah. Yeah. There's, there's an interesting, I won't go too far down this round, but
there's an interesting moment that happens when you really get into the writings of St. Augustine.
we all do. When he's involved in the Donatist controversy and he actually goes and meets
some Donatists, just individuals who are part of Donatist churches, I should say, these
schismatic churches. And he sees this love between the members of these communities.
even though they're schismatic communities.
And you can tell as he writes about it,
that it's kind of thrown his whole ecclesiology up in the air.
No, because he expected to see that they were just all wicked and stuff.
Right, because he's saying,
how can these people, if they're cut off from the church?
Right, they've schismed from the church.
We've cut themselves off with the church.
And so how can they possibly be manifesting the fruit of the spirit?
How can the Holy Spirit possibly be acting within them collectively, right, within a schismatic
community? Right. Right.
And so it's too, I'm not going further down as rabidol because I don't want to get into all of
of St. Augustine's early and late ecclesiology,
because that's-
But it is interesting, right?
So that he still had that understanding that
of the fruit of the Spirit that when you see these,
that means the Holy Spirit is there working
within a person and working within a community.
Yeah, because there's nothing good that doesn't come from God.
Right.
There's no independent good.
That's the thing.
And I mean, I'll just say, I know this is a bit of a rabbit trail,
but I think it's worth pointing out,
the sound because
especially those of us who have cultural and theological inheritance from the
Reformation, which probably everyone listening to this does on some level or
another, whether they get culturally at least. Yeah, culturally. Yeah, at least.
You know, there's this emphasis, like they'll take this where it says, you know,
all your righteousness is this filthy rags and this kind of thing. And they'll
basically say, well, someone might seem like they're doing good things
whatever, but it's actually just demonic garbage. Like, well, no, it's not. All the
things come from
God. You know, yeah. Oh, yeah. And from God. And you know, I'm going to wrap it around and make it not completely off topic.
So one question I get when I'm talking to people who have been in other Christian communities.
not the Orthodox Church for a long period of time.
And they're coming into the church and they're going to be
made it. And I say, well, this is
Christmas and to receive the Holy Spirit, a very common question I get is, so you're saying,
I haven't yet. Right. Right. Right. So you're saying, I didn't before. Right. The Holy Spirit is not
been acting in my life until I get Christmas, right. And the answer that is no. That is not what we're
saying, you wouldn't even be here. Right. Holy Spirit has not been acting in your life.
Right. That's why I said through St. Augustine's ecclesiology up in the air.
He didn't go and become a donatist. Right. Yeah. Right. And he still thought the donatists were
dead wrong. Right. Right. And at the schism needed to end and they needed to repent.
Yeah. Right. At least their bishops did. Right. But you can still acknowledge, not only,
and this isn't just, oh, hey, there are good people. You know, like, and that's that we're talking
talking about the good or not.
or something. The Holy Spirit is at work in the world all over the place. Right?
And the most obvious example of this would be from my perspective obviously as an Orthodox priest.
Right? I believe that the Holy Spirit brings people to the Orthodox church. Right?
Right? Well, when he brings him to the Orthodox Church,
they're outside the Orthodox Church.
Right.
So if the Holy Spirit only worked within the Orthodox Church, no one would ever come from
outside.
We'd be one of those little sects where you have to be born into it.
We'd be like the Protestant reformed.
Cheap Dutch shot, but they're not listening to this anyway.
So yeah, so it's not completely off topic, right?
So that isn't what we're saying, but the fruit of the Spirit are the evidence of that.
right? Why? Because those things aren't a human working, right? Right? Human love,
like what we call love today, which is at best romantic love. Right? We'll go too far
down the rabbit trail either of love, but there, there historically when people talk
about love, there's actually a Christian period.
Love meant a certain thing in the pre-Christian world. Then there is Christian love.
And then once you get to the high middle ages, that starts giving way to romantic love.
And then you get baby, don't hurt me. And then you get Freud. It becomes desire.
It's just the worst. It becomes desire. And now it's not even that.
Yeah, now it's okay to base things so at best you get like romantic love out of humans
But actual Christian love, right?
The kind of peace that comes from Christ,
not just, hey, that New Zealand Mellow,
he's from California, right?
The fruit of the Spirit are God working.
A human can't really do those things.
That's God doing that in and through a person.
And that's how we know the Holy Spirit is there.
And this is also over against,
not remain but
going to point it out, are more pedicostal friends, right? Who see certain kinds of miraculous
and quasi-miraculous manifestations as being the evidence of the presence of the Holy Spirit?
Hmm. And I don't think that's biblical. I think Biblically St. Paul tells us that the
manifestations of the Holy Spirit are the fruit of the Spirit.
Yeah.
And in fact he explicitly says, and he mentions some of those other things, that if he has those
that he doesn't have love, which is the first of the fruit of the Spirit, then it's all worthless.
Right. Right. And I think that's because if he doesn't have the fruit of the Spirit, then that shows that
those other things are coming from a different spirit, not from the Holy Spirit. Right. So rather than
judging the presence of the Holy Spirit by the
manifestations, I think biblically you would judge those manifestations by the presence of the Holy Spirit.
Yeah, it's a miracle, sure, but is there love and repentance and all that other stuff that we
actually expect to see from the Holy Spirit? And the scriptures are also really explicit that there
could be lying signs and false miracles and all sorts of things. So fruit of the Spirit is one
big piece of this. There's a
Another, I think equally big piece tied directly to it by St. Paul, but that gets because of the
Protestant cultural influence you mentioned, I think, gets vastly underplayed.
And that is that when you go back and read those new covenant passages in Joel and in Jeremiah
and then Ezekiel.
What you find is the other thing.
that the Holy Spirit is going to do is going to be to write the Torah on the hearts of those whom he
indwells. Yeah, and the reason why that's especially important is that you know, Pentecost as an old
testament feast because it was is the feast of the giving of the law. Right, that's when the covenant
it was given it Mount Sinai. Yeah. And so the new panic
an axe is when the new covenant is given. Right? And the new covenant isn't tossed the Torah in the trash. Right. We've got this new thing now, which is a little more ephemeral. So you can get away with more.
This is, right. This is the opposite.
This is the opposite.
And this is tied directly to the fruit of the spirit,
it's made clear the way that's usually interpreted is after the list.
says, against such things, there is no law. Right. There is no commandment of the Torah,
against those things, meaning the reverse that those things keep the law, keep the
in keeping. Yeah. Right. And so this is, if you read, this will strike you.
immediately if you go and and and don't use the ancient Christian commentary on scripture for this because everything's chopped up
right grab
Saint John Chrysostom's homilies on Romans
Some afternoon that you have to kill right and
Go through the passages where St Paul is talking about the Torah. It's talking about the law
and its relationship to the Spirit.
And what you will find is that St. John Christostom says over and over and over again
that the Holy Spirit empowers the Christian to keep the law.
Hmm.
The Holy Spirit empowers the Christian to keep Torah.
That's what he says.
That's...
Yes.
That's great for it.
Yeah, I mean, you know, there's...
I can't remember if any fusions were saying Paul says that you're saved for good work.
Yes.
Yeah.
Meaning that salvation has an actual goal.
Right.
And it's not to be saved.
And it is impossible.
Right. And this is in those new covenant passages.
Right.
That's the importance of this idea of the Torah being written on people's hearts.
The importance of it is and the no man having to teach his brother.
is that in their position, right, Jeremiah, the exiles happening, everything is coming crashing down,
the temples on fire, right? Jerusalem is being sacked, people are being taken as slaves,
right? As Ezekiel is writing, they're in exile, right? They can look at their own history
and say, hey, this whole us trying to keep Torah thing didn't work out so well.
Yeah, it didn't have what it takes.
Right. We didn't pull it off. Right. And we're not going to make it excuse and say, well,
we couldn't. What do you expect? Right. We're going to accept the consequences of our own actions,
and we're going to repent. Right. But the promises. Right. The promise of the spirit coming and
and doing people is that God is going to keep the Torah.
He's going to keep his commandments in and through us.
Because God can do it.
And for folks out there who are really well versed in Protestant Reformation theology,
I know this undermines everything.
But do the reading of the Scriptures on this.
And look at what it says.
Look at how the earliest fathers read it.
understood it, which is just this way. That this isn't a thing where Christ keeps the
law, so it keeps the Torah, keeps the law, keeps the commandments, so we don't have to.
Right. It's the spirit comes to dwell in us so that God keeps the commandments in and through us.
And then keeping those commandments doesn't earn us eternal life. You can't earn eternal life.
Yeah.
Not because we're humans and we're not powerful enough, not because there's some standard
and we can't meet it.
You can't do it.
It is not a possible thing.
Right?
It's not how it works.
It's like flying into space under your own power.
You can't do it, right?
Yeah, Kekeke and Torra doesn't give you eternal life.
It never works.
Right.
Never designed for that.
That's not what it does.
There's nowhere in the scripture that says, hey, if you keep the whole Torah, you will
have earned eternal life.
life. And to even think that way, you have to ignore the fact that like there's the whole
sacrificial system and everything that's in there for when you break commandments. Right?
So there's actually a whole bunch of people in Scripture, who the Scriptures say, kept
the Torah. Right. And they lived sinless lives. Yes. One of them is Saint Paul. Saint Paul
says that he himself as a Pharisee before becoming a Christian was blamed.
in terms of the Torah. Kind of throws a monkey wrench into a bunch of things, right?
Yeah. But that was never what the Torah was earning eternal life, right?
It's about, as we've talked about many times, you can go back to this episode,
Blessings and Curses, that kind of thing. But so those are the two core things that are not
unrelated. Right? The fruit of the spirit are the manifestation of the
presence of the Holy Spirit and they are how the Holy Spirit empowers the Christian to keep the commandments.
You know, God, which include one of the commandments, one of the primary commandments.
It's actually one of the Lutherist 95 Theses, believe it or not, is that we're commanded to repent.
You can't keep that commandment if you never sin.
Right.
Oh no, Torah paradox.
Yes.
That could be a t-shirt.
It's wore a paradox.
That could actually be like the opening act for Theophanec Glory Cloud.
That's right.
They're the band that just started out a little bit, you know, they're getting their feet wet.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
All right, well, all that said, we're going to go ahead and take a break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
take your calls on the next part of the Lord.
of spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
The Nativity season is a wonderful time to reach out to family and friends and wish them well
with a Christmas card. This Nativity, share your faith with them as well by sending a beautiful
the activity card from the engine.
faith store. All of the ancient faith Christmas cards are
vibrantly printed and feature images and words that point
their recipients to Christ. Purchase your favorite packs of
cards or several variety packs if you can't choose just one
favorite. Send your love and a bit of your faith this
nativity season with the help of Christmas cards from store
dot ancient faith dot com. We're back now with the Lord of
spirits. The Father and
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
You got your Christmas card set out yet, Father Stephen?
I'm going to take that as a no.
Anyway.
Hey, Father, are you there?
Do we lose you?
I think we must have. Oh, man, I can do this all by myself now.
All right. Well,
well, while we wait for Father Stephen to come back, I just wanted to make sure that everybody pays attention to the fact that we have a conference that we're going to be doing next October,
26-29-2023 at the Antioch in Village. It is the Lord of Spirits Conference.
He and I are going to both be speaking. We've also got our friends. I don't want to call them friends of the show because
That's not always a positive thing you know to say
What it's true
I love Bartirming with all my heart. Do you do yet? Are you like actual buds?
I wish no, yeah, I don't know doesn't even know I exist
He may know but yeah, so we're gonna have our friends father Lucas Christensen father David Subu
they're going to be speaking in process.
be some more, so it'll be a lot of fun. Go to store.hp.com slash events. And you can sign
up and you can see us in person and discover that we are in fact, as we said, in the very
first episode, two separate persons. Yes, you will see us in the same room at the same
time. That's right. Absolutely. I also, before we continue, want to do my own commercial.
Are you ready?
Okay, so if you are a big fan of this program and if you hear this live or in the next couple days
You need to go to Kickstarter
You need to search for historic vampire debate
Okay, and there you will behold a magnificent project
Which you will want to back are you involved in this somehow?
Huh?
No other...
than thinking it's awesome.
You're just a fan.
Oh wow.
And so two, to those of you who might want me to do a commercial
for your project, you could also go look,
it has to be at least this cool for me to do.
Wow, I'm seeing it.
Who knows what this is about, but anyway.
So go check that out in the next couple days.
Here you go.
But back to the topic at hand.
Yes. And hey, you know, everybody can give us a call.
Yes.
855 of free-do.
Is it still a free-do now that we're out of October?
I don't know.
I mean, it's always Halloween somewhere, right?
Could we temporarily change the number to like, ho ho ho, ho-do or something?
I'll have to look into that.
Okay.
I mean, you're the guy who works for the company.
You're the company man.
That's true. I am, but I don't I'm not really I don't do the telephony.
Well, I said a memo. I said a memo around. Yeah. Yeah.
You get that memo.
Trudy, get right on that please.
Yeah. Yeah. The memo. Get on making the memo.
So, um, in this second half of the program,
we're going to, as we said, we have a sort of Johanine structure here.
We're going to circle back around.
We talked in the first half about the indwelling, the filling of persons with the Holy Spirit.
And so now we're going to come at this from sort of the other angle and talk about anointing.
Oh, you know, with only you should say that, but we actually just got a call.
Alright, from someone who, yeah, they want to ask about
So, we will come from Tennessee, I think. William, are you there?
I am Father, can you hear me?
Yeah, we hear you. Welcome, William, to the Laura Spears podcast. So, what is on your mind?
So, my question is about the 19 oil used in the tabernacle.
I was researching the Genesis creation accounts as a temple construction narrative
and I read that there is a parallel between the seven days of creation
creation and the seven speeches that God gives to Moses for it.
Tabernacle, but the article didn't go into detail about those parallels.
And I was curious in particular about the connection between Dave Forrest creation of the Sun
Moon and stars and Genesis and Space Four of the Tabernacle where God and Strips knows
it's on a Nointing oil.
So one, is there a connection?
And hopefully that's a monosyllabic answer.
And two, what is it?
I'm just going to just punt that right over you to follow.
You're just going to punt?
Yeah, absolutely.
I have no idea.
I'm okay with that.
I don't need it.
The monosyllabic answer is yes.
Yes.
And the longer answer is yes.
No.
So this is a connection between, so the fourth day of creation,
We have to understand, and if you're a Lord of Spirits listener, you probably already do.
The Sun Moon and stars in terms of heavenly beings, adjelic beings.
Right.
And so this is referring to the coming into being of spirits.
and the oil.
the idea of anointing is connected that you will see some people who will try to
make this argument that there is some connection between the Greek word for
olive oil. Oh I know what you're going with this one. I know this one and the
Greek word from mercy. Right, right.
That is bogus. They're taking a particular conjugation of mercy, and a particular conjugation
for have mercy for the verb, and a particular conjugation of the noun, or declension of the
noun, for oil that kind of looks similar to an English reader. Yeah. I mean, but the two roots,
This is the other two words.
have no connection going back to linear B. I verified this.
Yeah, there's no etymological connection between them. They just happen to sound
similar, which is okay if you're, you know, making puns. Like that's fine.
It's okay to do theological comments based on puns.
Yeah, but just work like a magic.
Wordplay and stuff is fine. Yeah, there's a, but there is a direct connection
between oil and the
concept of grace. And one of the places where this connection is made explicit in the Orthodox
Church is in the prayer that a priest prays when he puts on his stole or his epiturkilian.
That talks about God's grace upon the priest being like the oil that was used to anoint Aaron,
right the high priest that makes that connection.
And grace in our understanding is divine action.
Right. Grace for us is not like a created substance as orthodox Christians.
It's not just God's mercy, right. It's not just his favor, but it is God actually acting.
Right. In the way that we've that we've been describing talking about the Holy Spirit.
So you may see where this is going now.
Right.
So.
So, divine grace is really the acting of the Holy Spirit, and a connection is being made
there with spiritual agency.
So this has been a very long, circuitous road to get to the point of when the objects are
are being anointed for the tabernacle.
They are being removed from the world outside where those objects even had spirits associated
with them.
That were because they're in the fallen world not good.
And by being brought in, they are now having spirits associated with them, the spirits who
serve in the Hevernley Tavernacle, the Angelic Hosts, right?
Who were...
along with us and participate in worship are being associated with them.
And the marker of that new association is the anointing of the elements of the tabernacle.
So that would be what I see as the connection between the two.
So into your question William.
It does, yes thank you.
Awesome, awesome.
Well thank you very much for calling.
Thank you very much.
All right.
Tell me the tell me truth halfway through that. Did you have any idea where I was going? No, okay?
This is all new to me and my I mean you repeat it to me later
Yeah, I think I think we recorded it so we did record it. Hey, that's that'll make it easier. I could go back and listen to podcasts
Who listens to podcasts? I
Don't listen to my own, but right yeah
So okay, listen to other people's
I used to listen to my own to kind of go back and you know critique what I was doing, but now it's just like it's just too much and I got
all this other stuff so yeah, yeah, the Shatner rule, right? He never watches any of his own stuff. No, he's never watched a single episode of Star Trek. Yeah.
The only movie he's watched is five and he had to watch it because he directed it. Oh, yeah, I wanted to watch it a little closer.
Whoa
What does God need with a starship?
You got to be honest.
You know, no one's perfect, even Shatter.
I have a, I have a, I have a warm, weird spot in my heart for Star Trek V. I don't know.
I'm not saying it's good, but there's something you need that kind of likes it.
Well, part of it too is there's been worse since, right?
It's a great, too.
And then we got Star Trek 6, which is the greatest of them all, in my opinion.
Yeah, I mean, it's like, you know, the star
more sprinkles were terrible then they came out with that sequel trilogy and it's kind of like
no I can put my thumb in for the jar jar you know okay well we're gonna lose a few more
listeners if we keep going out about Star Trek and Star Wars for too long that's okay and some
we'll gain some new ones yes true yeah right um so yeah so as um as I was saying we're
We're going to, in this second half, we're going to come back at this from the perspective
of anointing.
Right.
The anointing of people.
Okay.
In this half.
And then once we complete this circle, we'll see how those connect with the circle we made
last half.
So when you think about anointed ones, right?
What you hear the word anointed one, most folks, at least from a Christian background,
immediately think, oh, okay, anointed one, right?
Messiah, Mashiach in Hebrew, Christos in Greek, the anointed one, right?
The Messiah, right?
This sort of this singular figure.
in the old testament.
There are actually a number of different figures who are anointed.
Right. The king, right, is anointed when he's made king.
So this happens to Saul, happens to David, right, hands of Samuel, the prophet comes and anoints, right, the king.
And as we mentioned when we were talking about this after
the historically after the Western Roman Empire collapsed. In Western Europe the only thing
really providing any kind of overarching social order was the Western Church. And so as the Western
Church and a beleaguered populace is trying to figure out how to create new social structures
with the various
tribes of our barbarian ancestors. They took some socio-political cues from the Old Testament.
Right, and so you pretty quickly have the anointing of kings, some of these tribal chiefs and leaders,
right, are made kings by anointing, by a bishop, by the bishop of Rome,
sort of as the way of, right, well.
We'll default to the Bible in terms of form of government here, right?
But that brings with it that anointed status that anointing ritual, right?
Yeah, I mean, I think what in just a few months here will get to see Charles King of England anointed
Is this still a thing? Yeah, yeah
He was already
Not quite in an anointing, but there was that fellow who threw eggs at him
Yeah, did you hear about that?
What? No, but what's
to that, Granem. I'm not sure. Well, he was throwing eggs at him, and this is absolutely true. He was
sensed with a ban from the possession of eggs in a public place. Wow, which is just the most
British thing. That's so fair. You serve a now never possess eggs in a public place. I mean, that
It really feels like it's a python sketch.
Yeah, but it is absolutely true.
Wow, you cannot be trusted.
with eggs. Well, he had his hands. But so that is not an anointing, but no, but that's
where it comes from in terms of European kingship. So in a sense, every king, right, was an anointed
one, right? And that's probably pretty familiar in thinking, again, to most people from
a Christian background, because the Messiah is of course, right, we're familiar thinking
of the Messiah is going to...
going to be the king, right, the king of Israel, the
David King in particular. But, right, priests were also
anointed. Yeah. As part of the ordination, right, priests
and the high priest, any given time were anointed. And in our
next episode, two weeks from today, shortly before Christmas,
We're going to be talking about ordination.
and holy orders and that kind of thing.
And so we'll talk more about that there, right?
But for now, priests are also anointed,
and prophets were also anointed in some cases,
particularly when we see sort of prophetic succession
in the testament.
When we see like there are communities of prophets
or we see one profit sort of initiate or hand.
over sort of the prophetic ministry to another prophet.
That's often explicitly accompanied by anointing.
And so even though we're not necessarily now as Christians used to thinking about it this way,
in Second Temple Judaism for example, in the Second Temple period, there is an idea of
Messiah
right, that there are different ways in which the coming Messiah, the coming anointed one, is thought of.
So the one we're used to is one of those. The one we're used to is, this is the Messiah, the son of David, right, the king descended from David.
from David. Yeah. As God had promised to David, that's slightly different in chronicles.
and in first Samuel, or first kingdoms.
But the promise was either a child of your,
a son of yours will always reign on your throne
or a son of yours will always reign on my throne,
my being God's throne.
Yes, and this is definitely a porque no los dos.
Yeah, right.
So, and David then was both...
a model of the kind of person or the kind of king that the Messiah would be.
David is sort of presented as the ideal king, especially in person, second Chronicles,
which doesn't talk about the whole Bastille de Thing.
But it's also then the sort of fulfillment of the
the Dominic Monarchy, right, of that.
institution or that continuity leading from David himself, right? And yeah, again,
we're all used to that crisis born in Bethlehem, Royal David City, all that, right? But what's less
well known to us today, probably, is that there are also a lot of second-temple texts that talk
about it
a Messiah who is a priestly Messiah.
So a Messiah who is a son of Levi,
rather than a son of David, a Levitical Messiah.
And one of those sort of exhibit A of this tradition
is a text called the Testament of Levi.
Okay, so what's that?
Probably most people have not read that one.
Right, well it's part of the testament.
of the 12 patriarchs. Okay. But so Testament in this case, isn't like the old Testament or the
New Testament. Testament is a genre of second temple Jewish literature. And it's based around
Genesis 48 and 49 where Jacob, right, Israel the person, right, is...
on his deathbed, and he sort of gives these prophetic words to each of his sons. And so that
becomes a genre in the second temple period where all of these figures, there's a testament
of Adam, there's a testament of Abraham, there's a testament of Isaac, right? Everybody
gets testament. And so there's a collection called the testament of the 12 patriarchs and
Those are Joe.
of his brothers. And each of them has a testament. Each of them has sort of a sub-
document that's part of this larger text. But it seems pretty clear that the
individual testaments that are now in the testament of the 12 patriarchs
also circulated separately because we found individual ones in different places.
Okay. So the testament of Levi in particular, Levi, of course, is one of those
brothers.
Right? He's the one from whom the Levites descend who are going to be priests. And so
these are always written as if. So it's written as the frame is this is Levye
giving his parting words to his son. But of course, it's portrayed as prophetic. It's portrayed as
Levye is prophesying these things in advance. But of course, this is being written
and post. Yeah.
Exile and return long long after so it's a literary thing right right and so it includes things that happened in the intervening time and
Then things that are still future till to happen you from the time it was written right we found the testament of Levi on Mount Athos where
All 12 sweat testaments are preserved. We've also found it in the Dead Sea Scrolls
So this pre-Christian Jewish kind of schismatic.
community also had copies of the testament of Levi. So pretty widespread thing and something
that's been preserved by Christians. Yeah, good providence. Yeah. So yeah. And we also have a lot of
because of that providence we can compare, right? If anything's a later change or addition,
we can kind of figure it out. But so as one might expect to the testament of Levi, it's talking
about the priesthood.
Right, and how the priesthood was going to not go so well right over the course of the history of Israel and Judah.
But it's then prophesied.
A restoration of the priesthood and the temple.
And this is going to come now at this point that it's being written the second temple was there.
We'll talk about that a little bit more.
in the the third half. So this isn't restoration is in rebuilding. But there's going to be a restoration
of the priesthood in the temple and it has, in the testament of Levi, and this is reflected in
several other of the testaments of the 12 patriarchs too, there are two different Messianic figures.
There is a Messiah, a Messianic king, who's descended from Judah, and there's a...
a Levitical Messiah, a priestly Messiah who is descended from Levi.
And from the perspective of the testament of Levi, the Levitical,
the priestly Messiah is the more important one.
Yeah, right. Well, of course.
So at one point, it presents the priestly Messiah as being like the sun
and the kingly Messiah is being like the moon.
Right.
To give you an idea. So both very important. Right.
But
one more than the other. Right? And so this idea that there are these two
Messiahs with two different characters actually gets reflected in a couple
places in the New Testament. A good example of that is there's this episode
where after St John the Foreigner has been imprisoned by Herod, he sends
messengers to Jesus who ask him, are you the one or should we expect another?
Yeah, right, right.
And a lot of times people read that as, well, you know, St. John at the beginning of all four
gospels makes this really strong testimony that Jesus is the Messiah.
And so it's often read as if like he was doubting himself now that he was in prison.
Yeah.
Right.
But that's because people don't understand that this tradition was out there.
But St. John was really asking was, is there a second Messiah coming?
Right, he was not taking back his identification of Jesus as the Messiah.
He was asking for a clarification.
Right.
Are you one of two Messiahs?
Are you, how is this going to work now that you are the Messiah and you have come?
Right.
Because that was not immediately obvious.
There were different traditions at that time.
Right.
this being one of them.
And then
were probably at least generally familiar with the idea that that's king and priest,
the idea with with prophet that there was a strong tradition of Elijah returning.
Yeah, right, right.
And that that was directly related to the coming of the Messiah.
Right.
And again, this would be in at least, this would mean at least two kind of Messianic figures,
one of whom was alive.
What if who was a prophet?
Right.
And so we see this reflected in the New Testament when Christ asks his disciples,
who do people say that I am?
And what are the immediate answers?
Is some say Elijah?
Yeah, some say Elijah.
And also the questions regarding the identity of St. John the Forerunner.
Right.
You know, to say Elijah will come, Christ says, Elijah's already come.
You
uh, say, John the four-owner, right?
Uh, so
there are potentially up to three, right, Messiah's.
Uh, there is also a fourth Messianic figure
who kind of emerges
in Judea. This is my take on this, right?
Um,
so
the reason I'm couching this as my take is I think I can defend my take on this.
But I'm not going to take all the time now it would take to defend my take on this.
Okay. Right. So future blog post. Yes listeners, citations needed. Right.
So I'm not fully going to go into this, but for the sake of covering the ground, we need to, we need to mention it.
So there is another Messianic figure
that goes very far back in
rabbinic Judaism, and I think actually emerges in the second temple period. Although this
Messianic figure becomes more clearly defined as you move forward in time, right, within
Jewish communities, right? And this is not a thing that you see in Christian communities
And that's part of the reason for my...
take. Right. And this is sometimes called the Messiah bent Ephraim, meaning the Messiah
who's the son of Ephraim, as opposed to the son of Levi or the son of David. Right.
And so this is a figure. To understand this figure, you have to understand the tradition.
And I know we've talked about this on the show and I've talked about it in other places.
There is this prophecy, not just A prophecy, it's a theme in several of the prophets in the Hebrew Bible or the Old Testament in which Ephraim, meaning Israel, the Northern Kingdom, the Northern tribes, the Ten Tribes, are going to be reconstituted.
Right, that when God finally delivers Israel, when the Messiah comes, new covenant with all this
goes down, all of Israel will be regathered, meaning all 12 tribes, right? Because Judah
or Judea is like two and a half, right? So the rest of these tribes will be regathered.
That is like materially impossible. Right. If you're thinking of this in ethnic sense, right?
could that mean? Yes, right. Right. Because those
get resettled by the Assyrians, they intermarry over the course of a few generations, they disappear as distinct entities.
And so there comes to be a very strong tradition in Second Table Judaism that the way this is going to happen is through the Gentiles coming into some kind of covenant relationship with the Judeans,
Right with the Jewish people that will
cause them to take the place of those lost tribes and be part of the reconstitution of Israel.
One of the other testaments in the testaments of the 12 patriarchs, the Testament of Naftali,
everybody's favorite tribe because nobody could remember who or what it is.
But the test rate of daftily, which was one of the lost tribes, right?
That's why it comes.
up here. And I believe it's chapter 5 verse 8 but I might be reversing that, it might be
8 verse 5. Just explicitly says that like the Assyrians, the Babylonians, the whole list of
foreign nations will receive a part in Israel through the exile of the Northern Kingdom,
or through the captivity of the Northern Kingdom. So there's this tradition.
Right. And so...
There comes to be the later you go, right?
And the first place I know of where you see this clearly
is in second enek, which is sometimes called
salovonic enek, because we have it preserved for us
in salovonic.
That clearly seems to describe this figure.
A messianic figure, a messiah figure,
Who is going to bring about this
constitution, meaning who is going to bring these Gentiles in?
Yeah.
Okay, two sort of reconstitute those tribes.
And so second enich is written probably between 70 and 80 AD somewhere.
Okay.
So first century AD.
So Christians are around.
But not in Slavonic.
No, that is...
It's preserved in Slovak.
Yeah, yeah, we don't have the what probably Greek original.
We think it's actually Aramaic.
Oh, okay, okay.
Because there are some Aramaic words that are transliterated.
Oh,
but,
so, but it's written in the first century AD.
So it's written while there are Christians around.
Yeah.
And the all be it general description of this messianic figure.
who's not referred to as the son of Ephraim here
in to Second Enic, but he's referred to as just the man.
The man who comes.
Sounds a whole lot like Jesus.
Okay, there's a big rejected by his own people.
Going out to the Gentiles, bringing them to worship the God of Israel.
Right.
Okay, but the text is probably not written by Christians, right?
It is not written by Christians.
Not written by Christians.
So these are non-Christian Jews who have an opinion about Jesus.
That's my take on it.
And so maybe having some kind of mis-yanic role.
Right.
So there is, and I take, right, and like I said, if I was going to take another three,
four hours.
I could play this all out, but my take is that that tradition emerges within Judaism as a tradition of
non-Christian Jewish people who are looking at Jesus and at Christianity and at Gentile Christians
and even from the point of second
e-next seeing this as number one
beneficial to the Jewish people.
Because it decreases the hostility of those Gentiles toward Jewish people.
As turning them from idolatry, as turning them from sexual immorality.
So they're seeing these positive things from their Jewish perspective.
These are all net goods.
So see these good things that sort of like say to Guston seeing the fruit of the Spirit and the donatists right?
They're looking at
They're not ready to accept Jesus as the Messiah, right?
But they're seeing these things happen with the Gentiles.
And maybe he's their Messiah.
Right. And that's essentially what I think
the tradition is is maybe he's the Gentile Messiah
and our Messiah is still coming.
Yeah, interesting.
So that is a real thing
and I have talked to a North of the Jewish friend
who is
told me that that is still a live concern within Judaism.
Like that's not just an early tradition from before Judaism and Christianity
completely separated. That's through history. That has been an element of Jewish tradition and
a perspective. What do you do Jesus? Yeah. So but back to our main thrust here.
What connects sort of the idea of the King Limusiah, the idea of...
the priestly Messiah, the idea of the prophetic Messiah, right? Is the idea of restoration.
Right? So the Davidic Messiah is the one who's going to return the kingdom to Israel.
All right, he's going to restore the Davidic monarchy. He's going to restore sort of socio-political
Judea, Judea Israel, right? The way, for example, the testimony of Levi's...
the priestly Messiah, the priestly Messiah is going to come and restore the priesthood.
Reconsecrate the temple, restore the priesthood to what it should have been.
And Elijah is going to come to restore prophecy.
Right. And so the each of these.
This Messiah's however, these different Messiah's are conceived, they're coming to restore
sort of the job or the task or the purpose of that office.
But also then through exercising it, there is going to be this transformation of the world
through the Messiah being the king,
that's gonna bring about this transformation of.
the social order and the spiritual order, right?
Through the Messiah being the priest,
this is going to transform worship,
in a positive direction,
connected to that restoration.
So it's not just about restoring institutions,
but it's restoring institutions
and then through those restored institutions,
Transforming
the world bringing about a new messianic age.
Yeah, because I mean, it's the same dynamic then as being saved for good works.
We're not saved to be saved.
Right.
We're saved to be effective.
And yeah, folks who have managed to stay awake for the whole episode so far, hopefully all
of you who are driving, I'm probably seeing connections here.
Right?
in terms of what we were talking about, the Holy Spirit.
people and now what we're talking about with the idea of being anointed, right? Being the anointed one.
And those two are not something that gets put together like in later Christian theology.
Right. The idea of being filled with the spirit of the spirit coming to abide in someone and
being anointed is there right from the beginning exhibit A you can look at first Samuel or
our first kingdom, 1630.
Samuel and Oynne, David, he's filled with Holy Spirit.
Yeah, these things just go together and they always did, right?
So this isn't just sort of, oh, that seems kind of similar like these things are connected, right?
And they're so connected that when we get to the New Testament, so for example, in,
in St. John's Gospel in John chapter 1 verses 32 through 34.
The song...
that's given to St John the forerunner to identify Jesus as the Messiah as the Christ, right,
is that the Holy Spirit comes and rests upon him. Yeah. And it bides on him, right? St. John
has told the one who you see that happened, that's him. So the Holy Spirit is this messianic marker,
Right.
And so...
that connection isn't just a connection for these old testament figures who are
anointed which is again some certain individuals for particular tasks.
And it's not just Christ who is the anointed one, the Christ, the Messiah,
Par excellence who does all this. This is part of why Hebrews spends so much time
pointing out that Christ is both king and high priest.
Hmm, by the way.
And the way it restores the priesthood and restores worship.
But in the same way as what we talked about in the first half with the Holy Spirit,
now all Christians are anointed, not just literally with chrysum after their baptism,
but that's what Christian means.
in means. Yeah, right.
an anointed person. Yeah, it's interesting, you know, like in certain sectors of, I don't know,
especially pedocaustalism, anointing becomes largely a metaphorical term. You know, like he's
going to anointing to preach, which is, you know, like this idea that anointing has to do with
a particular function is good, right? But being empowered by the Holy Spirit for some
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, it becomes it becomes like well
person has an ability to do this thing. So that means they have an anointing from God.
It's like, well, did they get anointed? You know, which is, it's just pointed as being a kind
of a spiritual experience, you know, rather than any oil actually being transferred onto the person.
Right. Right. Where it's disassociated from the material and the, the community. Yeah. Yeah.
Right. So David wasn't just, didn't receive a kingly anointing. Right. In a spiritual sense. But
And actual...
profit walked up with oil and anointed him.
Yeah, put oil actually on it.
Right.
And so these things are connected.
Yeah, I think that's trying to be win some and ironic.
So win some though.
I think this is a difficulty.
not confined to our charismatic friends.
But I think this is an across the board issue in a lot of, but not all, but a lot of,
obviously it's back to something we were talking about the last episode about the Eucharist.
Part of the reason why it's so hard to number the sacraments and decide what is and isn't a sacrament,
or what is and isn't a mystery in the Orthodox Church,
is that fundamentally for us,
When we're talking about sacraments or mysteries, we're talking about God acting
through because that's what grace is, right? God acting through and within and permeating and
transforming the material, right? And that's something God does throughout the world all the time.
Right? So it's not that it's hard for us to identify things as sacraments. It's hard to identify
us to identify things as not sacraments.
sin, right? The likes, sin is very clearly not a sacrament, right?
Yeah. It's just like, you know, and I know I've mentioned this before on the on the show.
In one of his homely, St. Nikolay Villamirovich says, you know, what is a miracle? A miracle is just
a gift of God at which men marvel. But yeah, everything is, you know,
everything is a gift from God. Everything, therefore, that comes from God is a miracle. But we just
use that word to describe certain miracles. Right, right, right.
And so there's not that firm right distinction.
So again, other than sin, sin can never be a sacrament
contrast certain chance weight universities.
But yeah, almost everything else is. Whereas in a lot of, but not all,
Protestantism. When these terms are used
They're used in ways that do the exact opposite.
They're used in ways that separate the spiritual from the material.
Yeah, right.
Rather than seeing them as united.
Right. So, you know, before a baptism,
baptismal regeneration needs to be firmly denied.
Right. Yeah. I mean, I remember in my, this is doing anything.
but evangelical upbringing before almost...
every baptism in my witness there will be a little sermon about how baptism doesn't actually do anything.
Almost every time. And so, yeah, it's so they're divided. So it's not just the concept of
anointing without there being someone they're actually anointing someone, right? But it's
it's across the board with a lot of these things. Yeah, right. Where...
Right, right. And so that is a reaction to, and we talked about this a little bit last time.
Right. It's a reaction to a, uh,
wouldn't leave literal identification of those things.
Hmm. Right. So on one hand, you have someone who says, um,
we know who I'm talking about. But anyway,
you have someone who says that if someone hasn't been baptized and they die,
even an infant, right, that they go to hell.
for eternity. Right, right. So it's the actual side of the matter. That's it. If you've had it, you're good. If you have it, that's it. Right.
And the sort of terror that strikes into people for obvious reasons.
to the point where you've got folks trying to do baptisms on
you know, miscarried children.
Yeah, man.
Yeah.
Right? So you've got that.
You can understand reacting against that.
Yeah, right, right.
And say, look, God's not legalistic like that.
God's not bound by that.
Yeah, right?
That's the magical, that's magic.
That's magic.
You know, see?
Like the perfect God-
Immolation technique.
And to be fair to them, right?
The folks who take that view strongly would say,
well, God has bound himself to that.
Yeah, right.
by choice voluntarily. Right. So we've got to be fair. But I see you see reacting to that
strongly and saying, no, God's not bound by that. God's not restricted by that. God's love
is bigger than that. Right. That that isn't work. Right. But then you move too far in the other direction
of well, don't even worry about that. Right. Yeah. Like that's sort of generally unimportant. Right.
I see you'll yeah, yeah, I
I don't know, correct me if I get this wrong, but I recall reading one time a
critique of an ecclesiology that starts with the Holy Spirit as being an ecclesiology that is
ex-carnated, you know, because it doesn't, it doesn't, it's not an ecclesiology that involves
the material world, right, which is because Christ's incarnation is material.
You know, that the self-annoyingty prophet, the self-ordained bishop or whatever, you know,
someone who doesn't actually have to have a connection to anybody else, is this kind of
pneumatological ecclesiology.
You know, this reaction extremely in the other direction, like you're saying.
Right, right.
Or just, you know, you have an invisible church that has literally nothing to do with the
visible church.
Right.
They're literally two different things.
Yeah.
and no one has the power to...
communicate someone from the invisible church. Right. I mean, and this is what I mean, there's no
discipline, no church in right exactly in the in the reformation. You get a lot of anti-bishop stuff
and weirdly that pops up every so often, you know, anti-bishop stuff. It's it's really pretty
convenient not to actually be accountable to anybody. So yeah, so that that I think is a general trend
And like I said, that's not every Protestant person, that's not every Protestant group, right?
That's, but it's a lot, especially in America,
it's a lot of, especially American evangelicalism, right,
is in that category of being very,
there's a big disconnect between the spiritual
and the material in that regard,
rather than them being brought together.
And so that's the primary thing we're actually saying
in Christmas when we say that you're
anointed to receive the Holy Spirit
is that we're bringing those two things together.
At a point in time and so the the
Christ goes beyond rightful fills fills full. He doesn't just restore
The monarchy. He doesn't just restore the kingdom. He doesn't just restore the priesthood
He doesn't just restore
the temple and worship. He doesn't just restore prophecy, right?
Christ restores humanity
Hmm right through the incarnate.
And so Christians as anointed ones are in being baptized and
chrismated become part of this new restored and transformed humanity in
Christ that he brought about with his incarnation first and foremost.
But so this is what I'm sure I've said it on this show.
I forget where I say things.
There's things I say all the time.
but I'm sure I've said it at some point in the show that the idea of justification originally,
like in St. Paul, is has nothing to do with courts. It's much more like
justification in a word processor. Yes, line it up. Yeah, left justified, lined up on the left,
right? Justified, lined up on the right. Full justified, lined up on both sides, right? Put back in order.
Just as
restored, right? That order restored. And so when humanity is restored, we are put back in order,
right? As a person, as a created being. And then once put back in order, right? And repentance is
the ongoing nature of this, we also receive a calling. And we can also then be correctly
we describe.
as the elect, the chosen, the way the New Testament actually uses those terms, sorry, calculus.
Because the concept of being called and being chosen in the scriptures is always transitive,
meaning called is not a status.
Chosen is not a status.
It's not like USDA choice meat.
You're the best. You're the one God loves the most. It's always transitive. You're always called to something
Called to do something called to be something
Chosen for something
It's true across the board right Israel God's chosen people
Right that doesn't mean you were they were the ones who he loved the most
All right, the old testament.
They were chosen for a purpose to be a light to the nations, to the other nations, the Seventhy nations.
To be the nation through which he would bring forth the Messiah.
So Israel was chosen for purposes, for particular purposes, for things.
And the same is true of us. If you are a Christian, if you are an anointed one,
That means God is putting you back in order.
and he has called you and chosen you for particular things.
And in St. John's Gospel,
low and behold, Christ says to his disciples
that they had been chosen to bear much fruit.
We're right back where we ended the first half.
Yep, exactly.
All right, we're going to take another little break
and we'll be back with the third half.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord.
of spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Hi, I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and with my co-host, Father Stephen DeYoung,
I'm one of the podfathers behind the ancient Faith Radio live colon program, The Lord of
Spirits. Father Stephen and I have been blown away by the overwhelming success and popularity
of our lips.
show about angels, demons, saints, and yeah giants too. Apparently there's a real hunger
out there for content that addresses the spiritual reality that permeates all of creation,
in spite of the rampant materialism of modern society. But did you know that this programming
on ancient faith radio is only made possible by its listeners? Not only Lord of Spirits,
but all of the live shows on AFR, with Roxy Live, Ancient Faith, today, everyday Orthodox,
the scriptures live in the low.
and stewardship calling all of these owe their existence to the generosity of people like you.
Without your monetary support, there wouldn't be marathon discussions of Zeus or Hades or the
Nephilim on Thursday nights. There wouldn't be an ancient faith radio at all. Take the opportunity today
to add your contribution to those of the other faithful AFR fans who help keep shows like Lord of
spirits on the air. Participate in the Ministry of Ancient Faith Radio. Partner with us to bring the
Orthodox Christian faith to the world. Become a donor today by going to ancient
faith.com and clicking on donate in the upper right hand corner. Thanks in advance for your support.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
to young. If you have a question call now at 855-237.
Two three four six. That's eight five five a F radio
Thanks voice of Steve for back now the third half
It's always weird to me to hear those promos with my own voice on
Yeah, I wish you'd you brought me in on that one. Oh
Really this first yeah, cuz first of all
Background music I know we got to keep it public domain, right? But I mean
Okay, beat you can't dance to it though.
These are a little more base to much trouble.
It's gonna be exciting.
Well, it was still.
And second, second, most importantly,
if I had been there, so there were two of us, right?
You could have tweaked the ending a little and done the thank you for your support.
A lot of Bartles and James.
Oh, that's true.
Which would have really sold it right there.
It's true.
Man, that brings me back.
Yeah, wow.
Thank you for your support.
Yeah.
And I admit, although diehard is a great Christmas movie,
I admit that I preferred those Bartles and James commercials to Bruce Willis singing about
Seagram's Golden Wine Corps.
I have to say, up until this moment, I had never considered comparing those two things.
And I don't know to this day which one was Bartles and which one was James.
That's a good question. I don't know that either.
And if they were the actual people or actors playing Bartleson?
Yeah. I know.
Look up right in. I'll read all your emails.
Yes. Yes. Someone listening right now who's not driving.
Go ye to Wikipedia and find these answers.
Yes. You've been called to a very pointless purpose.
Is there a Bartleson? Is there even a Bartleson James?
Well, there must have been a Bartleson James at some point.
I don't know. It could just be names that they pulled out to.
could be there could be some kind of 18th century, you know,
rack on tours or something.
There you go.
Company and then okay.
All right.
Let's talk about the tabernacle.
What do you think?
Okay.
So, yeah, so this third half.
We're going to be moving to the other element which thanks to our caller in the
second half, which was William, I believe.
Right?
Yes, William of Tennessee.
Yes.
Will you...
of Tennessee. Not to be confused with his official title.
Tennessee Williams. Are you preparing him for St.
William? If we did really have Tennessee Williams, that would be amazing.
That would be amazing. I have to make him just sing into the phone.
Or Jack Daniels, Tennessee. We're just talking about liquor this
I guess. Um, so we already got into this a little talking.
about the anointing of the elements of the tabernacle.
But within the dedication of the tabernacle
and the dedication of the temple,
we see some of the same things in terms of anointing.
And we're going to see in terms of filling
with the Holy Spirit, the presence of God, the Spirit of God,
that we saw with people in the first two halves.
And so here's cycle three.
hopefully we'll connect this third spiral to the other two.
So the way the first one, yeah, I just had to say I couldn't help myself.
I looked it up.
Bottle and James are just fictional characters.
What?
They're not even real.
Yeah, they're based on, they're based on Ernest and Julio Gallo,
but they're fictional characters.
99% of my life, I was lied to.
I'm so sorry.
So I'll recover.
I didn't mean to demoralize you here at the end of the session.
I'll soldier on through this final half.
So the first one of these buildings, obviously, as we already talked about, a little is the tabernacle,
which gets dedicated in Leviticus chapters eight and nine after the construction is finished.
from which we have a couple of...
excerpts. We're not going to read you the whole of both chapters. Yeah. They're very involved.
If you want to go read them great stuff about waving parts of animals in the air and all kinds
of cool stuff. But yeah, we'll keep it short into the point now. Okay. Yeah. So Leviticus chapter 8
verses 10-11, then Moses took the anointing oil and anointed the tabernacle and all that was
in it and consecrated them. And he sprinkled some of it on the altar seven times and anointed the
alter
and all its utensils and the basin and its stand to consecrate them.
Okay, now skipping ahead to chapter 9, verses 22 through 24, then Aaron lifted up his hands
toward the people and blessed them, and he came down from the offering, from offering
the sin offering and the burnt offering and the peace offerings.
And Moses and Aaron went into the tent of meeting, and when they came out, they blessed the
people, and the glory of the Lord appeared to all the people.
fire came out from before the Lord and considered.
the burnt offering and the pieces of fat on the altar. And when all the people saw it, they shouted and fell on their faces.
That's what I do.
Well, the next chapter, fire again, comes out from before the Lord and they'd have an aboot.
There's two sons from here.
Right, but so you see this, you see this same kind of pattern, right? There is this, this dedication which includes anointing.
right, includes other things too, but so does our baptismal service. And that is followed
by being filled with, right, with the presence of God, right, with the Holy Spirit manifesting
himself in this visible and glorious way, the Theophonic Glory Club.
The Hoistler is present in the Tabernacle.
We see this at several points through the rest of the Torah, the cloud, how Moses would
go into the tent of meeting to meet with the Lord, and the cloud would descend, and no
one could enter.
And so when the time comes to dedicate the temple, right, there are a number of differences
between the building of the tabern...
of the building of the temple.
The biggest and most obvious one is that,
as we already mentioned in Exodus,
you get laid out twice in quick succession,
all the detailed measurements of everything,
what the tent curtains are supposed to be made out of,
what's supposed to be on the recipe for that incense,
right, like everything in all of this detail, right?
And in the temple you get kind of nothing, right?
you
So detailed instructions or non-detailed instructions or any of that.
It sort of David gets all the stuff and has a plan isn't allowed to execute the plan.
Solomon we think executed the plan according to what David did.
It's kind of iffy when you compare Chronicles and first Kings or Third Kingdoms.
You
But all that aside, and well, and I'll add, when Solomon goes and prays his prayer of dedication,
there's a certain discontinuity between his prayer and Yahweh, the God of Israel's response.
So, Solomon's prayer is stuff like grant all the requests of those who pray toward this building.
right which reflects one view of what a temple
is right. We talked about this, what do we talked about the view of the
ancient world that the temple itself was a body of a God. And then when God
responds, he basically says, well, look, I don't live in a building made by human
heads and I'm not contained by this. And you can't use this to control me. Makes
that all very explicit and that says but
And then God sort of condescends to come and be present in the temple.
And once he's made those important clarifications.
We see going forward, especially the book of Jeremiah,
that those clarifications did not necessarily sink in to all the people.
That descendants.
But nonetheless, God does consent to come and be present in the temple
for worship.
in Jerusalem and you can read the dedication in 1 Kings 3 Kings 8 and 2 Chronicles 7.
It talks about the same kind of glorious, the authentic glory cloud and manifestation
as the Holy Spirit, the presence of God comes and fills the temple.
And so this is this very powerful.
We know, look, it happened.
In Ezekiel, of course, from exile in Babylon, he was deported early.
There were several deportations to Babylon from Judah.
And he in his visions sees, yeah, way to God of Israel, leaving the temple before it gets destroyed.
Right, departing.
But so then an interesting thing happens because 70 years after the first temple is destroyed.
the people of Judah are allowed to go back and they end up founding what becomes the Persian province
and then the Greek province and then the Roman province of Judea, briefly the independent kingdom
of Judea. And of course they rebuild the temple and re-dedicate it. But when they do that in Ezra,
There's something that's notably absent from the description when you compare these descriptions to each other.
Yeah, so in Ezra chapter 3 verses 10 through 13, we read this,
and when the builders laid the foundation of the temple of the Lord,
the priests and their investments came forward with trumpets,
and the Levites, the sons of Asaph, with symbols, to praise the Lord according to the directions of David, King of Israel.
And they sang responsively praising and giving thanks to the
Lord, for he is good, for his steadfast love endures forever toward Israel.
And all the people shouted with a great shout when they praised the Lord, because the foundation
of the house the Lord was laid.
But many of the priests and Levites and heads of fathers' houses, old men who had seen
the first house wept with a loud voice when they saw the foundation of this house being
laid, though many shouted aloud for joy, so that the people could not distinguish the sound
of the joyful shout from the sound of the people's weeping.
For the people's shot.
with a great shout and the sound was heard far away.
Right. So there's joy, there's sorrow over the loss of the first
temple, right? There's worship.
But at least no visible sign of anything happening. Yeah,
unlike last time. Right. Nobody falling on their face, nobody
unable to enter because of the
clap.
of glory. Not that, right? And of course, then as we go forward in history, you can also look at
Nehemiah 2 11 through 20. As we go forward in history, that temple, the second temple and its first
form gets desecrated by Antichus the fourth epiphanies after he lost a war
with the telemaic ruler of Egypt.
He blamed his loss on the fact that the Giants refused
to worship the Greek gods.
And so that's why the gods hadn't favored him
with victory.
And so he went and sacrificed pigs on the altar
on the temple in Jerusalem to Zeus.
And so this obviously desiccrated the temple.
And it wasn't restored until during the Maccabeean Revolt,
when Judah the Hammer and his brothers came, and were able to liberate,
at least a good chunk of Judea from the Greek overlords and rededicate the temple.
and that's described in...
first Macapies. Yeah, this is in chapter 4, this is verses 52 through 59. Early in the morning on the
25th day of the 9th month, which is the month of Chislov, in the 148th year they rose and offered
sacrifices to the law of directs, on the new altar of burnt offering which they had built.
At the very season, and on the very day that the Gentiles had profaned it, it was dedicated with
songs and harps and loots and symbols. All the people found their faces and worshiped and blessed
to
who had prospered them. So they celebrated the dedication of the altar for eight days and offered
burnt offerings with gladness. They offered a sacrifice of deliverance and praise. They decorated the
front of the temple with golden crowns and small shields. They restored the gates and the chambers
for the priests and furnished them with doors. There was very great gladness among the people and
the reproach of the Gentiles was removed. Then Judas and his brothers and all the assembly of Israel
determined that every year at that season the days the dedication of the altar.
should be observed with gladness and joy for eight days beginning with the 25th day of the month of Chislov.
And so that's the origin of Hanukkah.
Yeah, right. Which has it started yet? I know it's
soon if it hasn't started yet. I am not sure.
But, right, so this is where the feast of Hanukkah comes from.
And you notice everyone's happy, it's good. They offer the sacrifices,
is, temples up and running again.
It says they did things according to the Torah, people fell on their faces in a worship,
but there's no record of nothing about the presence of God.
No theocratic glory cloud.
Right.
No expression of God's glory.
And so that temple goes on to get built out and added on to in part 2.
particular by Herod. Herod the Great starts the process
spent decades, right?
Building up around it, building the whole sort of platform
with the embankments, right, to support it.
So he can keep expanding it
as one of many building projects in Roman Gidea.
But there's never any record of any kind of manifestation.
of God's presence. And in fact, you start getting evidence to the direct contrary. A big piece of that evidence, for example, would be when the Roman general Pompey comes to annex Judea, because those same macabees, we're just reading about the Asmodeans, made a treaty with the Romans to help keep the Greeks away.
and that didn't work out so swell.
Yeah, it's so, it's told Judea to the Romans essentially is what happened. Yeah.
And so the Romans came in and annexed it, but they sent the general Pompey to do that. And
when he arrived, he insisted on going into the Holy of Holies.
Because no one was allowed to go back there and the Romans considered it a great mystery, right?
what was back there. And so he used it
the Roman legions plowed past the priest, went into the temple, went into the holy of Holies,
not only saw nothing there, when he went in, but nothing happened to him.
Yeah.
Which I'm sure he followed.
He followed his head.
Was it slain in the spirit?
literally none of no death by holiness no
these things happened, right? He just walked back out, right? And told all the Romans,
wow, that's weird. Nothing's there. In the temple, I don't know why they didn't want anybody
to see that there was nothing there. So all of this, you know, in the popular mind of Judean
people that they're aware that there's something wrong. And this created...
for a wide swath of different Jewish groups in the second
temple period, different levels of ambivalence and sometimes
outright rejection of that temple.
So like the folks at Kumron who wrote the Dead Sea Scrolls rejected it completely.
Said it was not a legitimate temple at all.
The Sadducees, of course embraced it because they controlled it.
high priesthoods. They're under sort of...
of wealth. So they were great with it, right? But so there were these different theories as to what
the problem was. So there are folks like, as we saw in the testament of Levi, right, reflected
there who thought the problem is the priesthood. These were to be the Zadakite priests, the sense of
Zadok were to be the high priest of the new temple.
These are not them, even though they call themselves Sadducees,
Sadduke, right?
The Zatakites, they're not really.
And they're corrupt, incredibly corrupt.
And so that's the problem.
And so they saw, this is part of what they understood,
as we mentioned in the second half,
that this Levitical Messiah, this Presley Messiah
would fix the priesthood and by restoring the priesthood
and purifying the priesthood,
with thereby restore and purify the temple.
Right. One of the signs that that had happened would be the presence of God, the glory of Lord returning to the temple.
Right. The Pharisees, like I said, this ambivalent relationship, they thought, well, this is really the temple. Right. They didn't reject it completely.
But the problem was that sort of the land.
They're around the temple Jerusalem.
They weren't fond of the Sadducees either.
We're defiled because of the sins of the people,
the uncleanness of the people.
Yeah, which is why they're obsessed with
trying to get everybody to keep the law perfectly
and then God can come back.
The strictness of the Torah was, hey,
and there's a certain logic to it, right?
Like we got sent into exile in the first place
because of our sins, our unrepentant sin, right?
So if we want God to come back and dwell among us,
You don't get our-
together and repent and keep the commandments. Right? So but that and that is part that ambivalent
relationship is part of why the party of the Pharisees was able to survive the destruction of the
temple and become rabbinic Judaism is that they were already kind of detached from that temple.
Right. Right. And so it was not as great as loss. Right. The Sadducees ceased to exist.
because what the temple's got because that's all they had.
but the Pharisees are able to keep moving.
But in general, we could say that in some way,
when the Messiah comes, he'll fix this, right?
Whether it's priestly version, whether it's right,
that that would be the fix, right?
That would be the thing that would restore
God's presence dwelling among the people.
So the perspective.
that the earliest Christians, meaning the Apostles, take in the New Testament, is that that is
in Jerusalem certainly a temple, but that the New Temple, the promised New Temple, the New Temple
of the New Covenant is actually Jesus. It's actually Christ Himself. Yeah, right, is the temple.
And they're drawing on what was already a
strong current in Second Temple Jewish thought, and that is that the temple
described by Ezekiel, back to Ezekiel and exile. The last probably about a third
of the book of Ezekiel is his description of this temple, this new temple. And
part of that description is about the glory of the Lord entering into that temple, by the way.
Yeah.
So, I mean, that was an explicit part of, you know, and so that's also a piece, right?
Well, there certainly isn't a Seeky old temple because the glory hasn't entered it.
But there already was within Second Temple Judaism.
There was never an attempt at any of these stages, right?
And maybe with Ezra and Niha Maya, they couldn't do it.
They didn't have the resources.
But the Maccabees probably did.
And Herod definitely had the resources to build whatever he wanted to.
None of them try
to actually follow the measurements and build Ezekiel's temple. So there's a sense that you're
not supposed to do that. Right, there was no attempt. Because there was already this idea in
second-templar Judaism that Ezekiel's temple, this final temple, the sort of eschatological temple,
is a temple not made with human hands. Not that humanity somehow sullies it,
And as we saw the Tabernacle...
was sort of made by God with human cooperation, right?
Because the Holy Spirit was involved.
But human hands not involved, right?
That's what this new temple will be.
And so that means it's not any physical temple
that anyone's going to build in the city of Jerusalem.
That idea was already there.
And so, St. John does this in particular,
but it's really a theme through most of the new tests.
that Christ is, right, his body in particular.
This is the place where the Holy Spirit,
this is the place where God comes to dwell among his people.
It certainly is in the person of Jesus Christ.
And St. John is the one who, you know, in all the gospels,
you get the saying of Jesus, you know, destroy this temple
You don't destroy this temple an hour of building in three days.
Right, you get it in various forms.
But St. John is the one who adds sort of the parenthetical note.
He was speaking about the temple that is his body, right?
Just in case you were, like, it didn't click for you.
Let's hammer this home.
He's talking about his body.
And so,
and this is, this is also why St. John, at the end of the book of
revelation.
He makes the point that in the New Heavens and the New Earth there is no temple because God in the Lamb dwell among them.
So Christ is the temple, so there's not a literal Ezekiel's physical temple that shows up at the end.
That Christ is that temple.
and so crisis both
the Messianic person, the person who is the anointed one. He is also the temple, which was also anointed.
So he restores the temple himself. And so again, for those still awake, hopefully all of you driving at this point in the
That was us, right?
We.
We end up in a very similar place to where we ended up at the last two halves because of course
Christ is the fulfillment of this, right? But
Christians, every Christian,
is also described as the Temple of the Holy Spirit, as very directly by St. Paul and 1 Corinthians 619.
Right? Your body is a temple of the Holy Spirit. And so
Christians bodies are anointed to become.
the temple of the Holy Spirit. To be filled with the Holy Spirit. And the temple, the tabernacle,
and then the temple, they're the place where the presence of God is in the world in a unique way,
right? Because God is present everywhere, but not in the same way everywhere. Right. Right. So it's not,
he's not in the temple as opposed to everywhere else. Right. But he's there in a unique way. And so the
the presence of
God is in the world in a unique way in his people, in Christians.
Right?
So we've talked about, we're looping around back to Genesis.
We're ending where we began.
We've talked about before how the calling, the thing for which Adam and Eve were chosen
was to go out of paradise into the world and take paradise, the temple which was paradise
with that.
to go and continue putting the world in order and filling it with life, right, to turn the
whole of creation into a garden, to a well-tended garden that is abundant in life. And so the way that
this happens now is that anointed Christians as the temple, as paradise in whom God dwells,
are sent out into the world.
to bring God and to bring paradise to place where God dwells with them.
And we made this big deal in this half about this contrast between the dedication of the tabernacle in the first temple
and then the dedications and rededications of the second temple.
Right and uh to uh to quote at least
the King James translation of the long ending of Mark, the signs attending, right, when that happened,
right? So earlier, we took a little bit away from our charismatic friends, now we're going to give
a little back. This is part of the function of what's going on with all of the signs and miracles
that we see in the Gospels and Acts.
Why all this?
These are the indicators that just as the lack of any kind of signs pointed to the lack
of God's presence in the rebuilt temple, the presence of these signs surrounding Christ,
who is the new temple with the presence of God, and Christians who are the temple of
the hoist spirit. Is an identification in
an indicator, right, that these people are the place, right, that Christ is the
temple, the fulfillment of the temple, and then that Christians, these people are
the place where God is dwelling. Are the place where interaction with God
happens, right, through these people. And so these signs are not limited to
no.
Exorcisms feel.
things, raising the dead, et cetera, et cetera. They do however include those. Yeah. Right. So charismatic friends
compared to us orthodox, your cessationists. We still have saints raising the dead and stuff.
Oh, you know, what's the, there is, what was the guy's name? Wigglesworth claimed he could raise the dead. Oh, I don't know if he did or not.
or not but um so
So all that is still part of it, right, to this day. And it especially happens when you look at church history, right?
The frequency those things become the most frequent
during times when the gospel and
through the gospel Christ is coming to a new part of the world.
That's when the
these kind of identifying signs are the most frequent.
You could go and just do a quick,
it would be interesting to do this in detail for somebody actually.
Go and study how many enlighteners of different places were also wonder workers.
Yeah, right.
But so it includes that, but it's not limited to that.
And sometimes we limit miracles to that, right?
Repentance is a miracle, salvation is a miracle.
Right.
Someone who is deeply lost in sin, repenting and coming to Christ and having their life transformed,
is actually a much, much greater miracle than someone being healed.
Right.
Physical, physical disease, right?
Or even somebody being physically raised from the dead.
Yeah.
I mean, we have scenes, let's say that.
It's, um...
So those are also miracles that accompany this.
And the fruit of the Spirit in their full embodiment
as we've talked about to wrap this all up together.
Armoraculous.
The kind of love, the kind of joy,
the kind of peace that it's had in Christ,
that is not a human origin, right, is likewise miraculous.
So hopefully through these three cycles.
I don't know if we'll ever structure an episode this way again, but there are these three cycles
we've connected some of these things for folks.
Or just made them dizzy.
One of the two.
Hey, hopefully no one ran off the side of the road.
Spend them right around like a record.
Like a record.
Well, I don't have a lot of voice left, but the couple of things I wanted to kind of
point two at the end.
You know, especially we're talking about sacraments there can be because of our cultural theological inheritance
At desire to you know, ask the what question a lot. I mean, and I get it
I mean we want to know what what is this right and and and you know someone who's been
Charismated what is he?
and
asking what exactly
Charismation is all that sort of thing but I
I think if we-
If we leave our questions there and that's the most important thing to us, I'm not saying
it's not important, it's important, sure.
But if that's the most important thing, then we have a problem because there's a purpose
to these sacraments, there for something.
And occasionally we get questions that are like this about a lot of things, like the
perennial question of what exactly is a giant, right?
the most important thing.
you should know about a giant is not what he is,
but rather what he does and how he functions in the world,
just like saints.
What's really important about them is not what they are,
how exactly they got to be a saint,
or the canonization process, or that kind of stuff,
as important as those things are.
The most important thing about a saint is the way
that he shows forth the presence of God in the world.
And Christmas is exactly this.
Recreation.
made it for something. When you're
cremated in the Orthodox Church, it's
not to make you the member, a member of
an institution. It's to make you a
member of Christ, which is not a
membership in the sense of having a
card. It's like being the members of
a body. We've talked about bodies a
lot on this podcast. You know that
a body is this collection of powers
and potentialities through which
You
a person operates.
And the body of Christ is through which Christ operates in this world.
We are His body, we are His members.
And the purpose of Christmas is to do the things that we've just been describing
in the past few hours.
You know, we're a Christmas for something.
We're a Christmas for something.
In order to receive a commission, you know, it's not a possession or a status.
It's a task.
you know, it's an empowerment for something.
And Christian life is much more about that for what it's for,
than it is about the precise means
or definitions of how you get to that for.
It doesn't mean those things don't matter,
but when we become extremists in one direction or another by saying,
Oh it all just doesn't matter at all, you know, I feel the spirit so it doesn't matter, you know.
or we become an extremist in the other direction, you say, well, only through the following very precise set of formulae, does this work?
In both cases, we're kind of becoming magical thinkers, right?
And that's idolatrous as we've said many times, it's idolatrous. That's the problem.
So we're saved for something, you know, we're not we're not saved so that we can be saved we're saved so that
we can be holy in this world so that we can show forth the works, the presence, the love of God in
this world, so that the world can be healed and so that through him the world might be saved.
Father?
So a catacumin in my parish who is an adult who is a couple decades younger than me.
making me feel very old. So I secretly despise him for that. But otherwise is a
good kid. Asked me for some clarification about something we talk about a lot of
the show. Which is, for example, in the episode about spirits, we talked about how
there are spirits active in groups and communities and places and workplaces and
and institutions, right?
And we talked about sort of,
there being an exorcism replacing one
that is dedicated to human destruction
evil with one that is good and leading the salvation.
You're sort of asking me what that concretely looks like
for a person, right?
Who's like going to work in a job
or going to school at a school
was part of some other
kind of community, right? Like what does that mean? And I think what are the major
foci of what we've been talking about tonight is that every one of us as a Christian
is an anointed one, is someone who has the Holy Spirit working within us and through us,
carries the Holy Spirit.
Spirit of God with us wherever we go.
And a lot of times this gets expressed negatively, right?
What it's talked about in popular circles.
This is, you know, the Holy Spirit dwells in you are you going to go into a movie theater at an R rated movie?
Right? Or are you going to hang out with these Nair duels?
Are you going to...
smoking, chewing, and dance with girls who do.
And there is precedent for that.
I say that obviously with some levity,
but St. Paul comes out and asks,
will you join the members of Christ to a prostitute?
So there is biblical warrant for that kind of negative
approach to that.
But I think very neglected and more important
is the positive element of that.
that bringing the spirit of God with us out into the world, right, out of paradise and out into the world.
The world where there is chaos, the world where there is death, the world where there is darkness is like carrying a candle with us out into the darkness, right?
Like carrying a torch with us out into the darkness.
This is what I think St. John is getting at in first John, 4-4 when he says,
greater as he who is in me than he who is in the world.
in the world. There's a lot of spirits out there in the world, but the one who was within us
is greater and more powerful infinitely than any of them. And so on a very practical level,
when we come into a place, into a community, into our families, into our workplaces, into our
school communities, whatever it is. When we come there, and we bring the Holy Spirit with us,
not just sort of de facto because we identify.
clients, Christians. But in the sense that we're working in repentance and faith to bring
out and bring to maturity the fruit of the Spirit in our life, that that presence and activity
of the Holy Spirit begins to transform the communities and the world around us. And precisely
this way by driving out those other spirits, by driving out those other agencies, those other
and other things that are acting upon us and the people we love and the people we work with and the people we spend time with.
It pushes them out and replaces them with the presence of God Himself.
When we bring love into a situation where there is hatred and bitterness and anger, and it's real love.
you love. It's not us saying
platitudes, it's not saying, hey, can't we all just love each other?
You know, don't worry, be happy.
But manifesting the love of God toward people,
the real deep love and compassion and kindness and care of God toward people.
When we bring a real sense of peace and we make peace between people,
Right.
Then the spirit that's then been there, putting people at odds.
with each other. Spirits of dissension and bitterness, right? They're driven out.
Then, you know, behold how good and how pleasant it is for brethren to dwell together in unity.
And this is the concrete way. It is concrete, right? We can't change the world in the sense that I can
and point my finger by magic at a chair
and turn it into a table.
But as we've talked about.
So the world we all live in is made up more of our perceptions and intuitions and experiences
than it is, you know, those hard and fast things that we can't change.
And so through just one person who's honestly striving every day to follow Christ, both
in keeping commandments and in repenting when not.
One of the most powerful ways to train...
to completely transform a social dynamic is to apologize,
to actually accept the blame for our failures,
to actually being honest about them and apologize.
So repentance is a big part of this too.
But one person doing that can transform a whole system,
can transform a whole workplace, can transform a whole dynamic.
Right?
And it's when we do that, that people see Christ in us,
It's when we do that, not win arguments.
that people are drawn to find Christ in His church.
And as they do that,
they start to become Christians as well
and they start to make an honest effort to follow Christ.
And some of us who have been Christians
are whole lives but maybe aren't making an honest effort right now,
are inspired by seeing those who do
to start making further efforts ourselves.
And slowly, slowly, peace by peace,
You
big systems can be transformed. And if you don't believe that's true, I will once again point
you to history where a bunch of peasants and fishermen in a backwater of the Roman Empire
took them 300 years, but completely transformed society, culture, politics, everything.
Just by each one of them being willing to follow Christ, whether that meant life or death,
whether that been GOR-
dishonor, but they made that honest effort every day. And through them, the spirit, the
Holy Spirit, the Spirit of God came to fill a whole empire and change it. And it can
do that again. But we don't start by trying to stage some kind of Christian revolution.
We've seen how that goes, right? We do that by each of us in our place, in the place
God has put us.
And the family he's put us in, and the occupation he's put us in, and the church community he's put us in.
Making these everyday day to day efforts to love, to be a peace,
experience real joy, to be kind, to be good, to be gentle,
to be faithful, to exercise self-control.
Those are my final words.
Amen.
Well that is our show for-
Thank you for listening everyone.
If you didn't get through to us live this time,
we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordOfSpirits at ancientfaith.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page,
or you can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordOfSpirits.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays
of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
Next time, holy orders.
And if you're on Facebook,
you can like our page, join our discussion group.
might be the only removable thing on Facebook.
Leave reviews and ratings everywhere, but most importantly, share this show with a friend who is going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.AxfordFafe.com,
support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air,
historic vampire debate.
Kickstarter.com.
Thank you, good night and God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
than thousands of thousands.
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
Welcome to Eastern Christian Insights with Father Philip Lamasters.
Homelies from St. Luke Orthodox Church in Abilene, Texas.
Father Philip.